<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A spiritual portion of heavenly treasure bequeathed by Mr. William Wheeler, late minister of the Gospel, and pastor of a church of Christ at Cranfield in Bedfordshire, as his last legacy to his wife and children.</title>
            <author>Wheeler, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 126 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96299</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38875905</idno>
  <idno type="VID">152495</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248570495</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42889</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">38875905</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96299)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152495)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2299:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A spiritual portion of heavenly treasure bequeathed by Mr. William Wheeler, late minister of the Gospel, and pastor of a church of Christ at Cranfield in Bedfordshire, as his last legacy to his wife and children.</title>
                  <author>Wheeler, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Contains marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Title within ornamental border.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>"A spiritual portion of heavenly treasure, bequeathed by Mr. William Wheeler ... as his last legacy to his children" (p. [19]-72) has special title-page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures:</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Spiritual life --  Christianity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:1"/>
                  <p>A Spiritual Portion OF HEAVENLY TREASURE, Bequeathed By Mr. WILLIAM WHEELER, Late Minister of the Gospel, and Pastor of a Church of Christ at <hi>Cranfield</hi> in <hi>Bedfordshire;</hi> AS HIS Last Legacy TO HIS Wife and Children.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the year 1670.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:2"/>
                  <head>The EPISTLE.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My dear WIFE,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THis little Piece did I fore-cast to leave in a faithful hand for thee; that if God would, it might be some Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and Support to thee after my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; and adde some relief to thy drooping Spirit, having so newly parted from thy dear Husband: And though peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon the first cast of thine Eye over it, it may cause thy tender heart to relent the more, to hear thy dead Husband speaking to thee, as it were out of his Grave; yet I hope when thou hast well weighed the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and the comfortable Arguments there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained; it may be no little comfort and refreshing to thy mind at present. And also if God will, it may be of good use to the remaining part of that little time that thou hast yet to live in this Vale of Tears.</p>
                  <p>Now the Lord add his Blessing to it, that it may do thee good. The Reason why I did not shew it unto thee in my life-time, was, Because I thought it might take so much the more impression upon thee for thy
<pb facs="tcp:152495:3"/>good and comfort, by how much the more it should come new and unexpected to thy hand, and that at such a time when thou never expectedst to bear any thing more of thy Husband in this World; that then he should as it were come again to thee, and afford thee one half hours discourse for thy comfort in this little Book. And for the occasion that put me upon it, thou mayst perceive that, in the Preface of that little Piece I have writ to my Children.</p>
                  <p>Dear Wife! I shall say no more: The Lord be ever with thee, and plant his fear more and more in thee; and replenish thy heart, and my Childrens, with his Grace, and the sweet Knowledge of Christ-Farewell, till I see thee again.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thy late dear Husband,</hi> William Wheeler.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:152495:3"/>
                  <head>A Spiritual Portion OF Heavenly TREASURE. OR, The Last Legacy of Mr. <hi>William Wheeler,</hi> to his WIFE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MY dearest Wife, and faithful Friend,</l>
                     <l>For thee (my Love) these Lines I write,</l>
                     <l>To leave with thee, that stay'st behind,</l>
                     <l>When I am taken from thy sight.</l>
                     <l>And now, because thou canst not see</l>
                     <l>My face, not hear my tongue to speak,</l>
                     <l>Which doubtless will be sad to thee,</l>
                     <l>And make thy tender heart to break.</l>
                     <l>I here have left my tongue behind,</l>
                     <l>To speak to thee when I am gone;</l>
                     <l>And comforts yeild unto thy mind,</l>
                     <l>When upon earth my Glass is run.</l>
                     <l>Dear Heart! It wounds me most of all,</l>
                     <l>That thou shouldst grieve thy tender heart,</l>
                     <l>And drink down Wormwood mixt with Gall,</l>
                     <l>And put thy self to needless smart.</l>
                     <l>Don't so, my Love; there is no cause;</l>
                     <l>'Tis want of faith in them that do:</l>
                     <l>I am deliver'd from the Jaws</l>
                     <l>Of Death, and gone to Heav'n too.</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:152495:4"/>
                     <l> Consider,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.13.</note> Love, thou must not mourn</l>
                     <l>As those poor Souls that hope have not;</l>
                     <l>Thou know'st that to a Kingdom born</l>
                     <l>I was,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.32.</note> and to it now am got.</l>
                     <l>And thou, my Love, unto the same,</l>
                     <l>Shalt, after a few days, attain;</l>
                     <l>To glorifie that blessed Name,</l>
                     <l>And both together there remain.</l>
                     <l>Don't grieve, my Love; the time is short,</l>
                     <l>Till we again in Bliss shall meet,</l>
                     <l>Upon the Top of <hi>Sion</hi>-Fort,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And walk the golden-paved street.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.21.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The time is short, I say again:</l>
                     <l>Let such as Wives or Husbands have,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29, 30, 31.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As if without they did remain,</l>
                     <l>So be, if they their Souls will save.</l>
                     <l>Again (my Love) I am not lost,</l>
                     <l>But hid a little from thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>To take a slumber in the Dust;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in the Morning I shall rise.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 49.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>A little while thou seest me not;</l>
                     <l>After a little while again,</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt see me stand up in my Lot,</l>
                     <l>With thee, amongst that Heav'nly Train.</l>
                     <l>And truly (Dear) if thou didst see</l>
                     <l>The truth and case, as 'tis indeed,</l>
                     <l>Lively presented unto thee,</l>
                     <l>Of sighing thou wouldst see no need.</l>
                     <l>'Tis but the darkness of thy mind,</l>
                     <l>If ought <hi>(my Dear)</hi> thy heart perplex;</l>
                     <l>If thou didst see things in their kind,</l>
                     <l>Thou wouldst not thy poor heart so vex,</l>
                     <l>Didst thou but see all things below</l>
                     <l>To work for good,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note> for thee and me,</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152495:4"/>
                     <l> And things above in Heaven also,</l>
                     <l>Thou wouldst not for me troubled be.</l>
                     <l>Didst thou but see both Death and Life,</l>
                     <l>True Servants for thy greatest Joy;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Twould end within thy thoughts the strife,</l>
                     <l>And from thee take what doth annoy.</l>
                     <l>Dear Heart! for us it is a shame,</l>
                     <l>That Christians do profess to be,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And lively hope have through his Name</l>
                     <l>Of Life and Immortality;</l>
                     <l>To look on Death as such a thing</l>
                     <l>As others do, that faith have not;</l>
                     <l>Since Christ hath taken out the Sting,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 55.57.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And the Hand-writing out did blot.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 2.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Dear Love! give ear to what I say;</l>
                     <l>We do not die as other men;</l>
                     <l>An Earthly House we down do lay,</l>
                     <l>To take an Heav'nly up again.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fie, fie, for shame! what Christians we!</l>
                     <l>That should indeed be men of faith;</l>
                     <l>And yet at parting wounded be,</l>
                     <l>Knowing what Scripture to us saith!</l>
                     <l>Alas, how should we ballanc'd be,</l>
                     <l>For Life and Death, and all alike,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Both for our selves and others free,</l>
                     <l>Ev'n whom Death's Sergeant please to strike!</l>
                     <l>Methinks I hate those dreadful thoughts</l>
                     <l>That in the hearts of some do dwell,</l>
                     <l>That look on parting as a Ghost,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Job</hi> 18.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And Death as black as if 'twere Hell.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Methinks it doth disgrace the Blood</l>
                     <l>That for us our sweet Jesus shed,</l>
                     <l>As if his death had done no good,</l>
                     <l>Nor broke the deadly Serpents Head.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152495:5"/>
                     <l> Methinks that from the work so great,</l>
                     <l>That our thrice-bless'd <hi>Redecmer</hi> wrought,</l>
                     <l>It takes away the life and heat,</l>
                     <l>And makes it as a thing of nought.</l>
                     <l>Methinks (my Love) redeemed Ones</l>
                     <l>Should never be so sad in mind,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Since whosoe'er by faith o'ercomes,</l>
                     <l>A Crown of Life in Heav'n shall find.</l>
                     <l>And nothing they on earth can loose,</l>
                     <l>That lose not Christ their chiefest Joy;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.39.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who under's foot does th' Serpent bruise,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all things else that can annoy.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Away (my Love) drive from thy heart</l>
                     <l>By faith, thy sighs and sorrows all,</l>
                     <l>And all that pinching needless smart;</l>
                     <l>And in thy Joys and Comforts call.</l>
                     <l>For all is thine, if Christ be thine;</l>
                     <l>Life,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22.</note> Death, <hi>Apollo, Cephas, Paul;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Things present, things of future time;</l>
                     <l>O He's (my Dear) thy All in All.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 3.7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in his hands thy Husband still</l>
                     <l>He hath,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.</note> and back he would him send</l>
                     <l>To thee, thy heart with joy to fill,</l>
                     <l>If it unto thy good might tend.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay more, himself, even from his Throne</l>
                     <l>Of Glory, would to thee come down,</l>
                     <l>(So great's his love unto his own)</l>
                     <l>If for thy good it might redound:</l>
                     <l>And dwell with thee, as once he did</l>
                     <l>With <hi>Mary, Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If it expedient were,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 16.7.</note> and rid</l>
                     <l>Thee from thy sorrows, ev'ry one.</l>
                     <l>But, Love, because he more can do</l>
                     <l>In Heav'n for his, than if on Earth,</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152495:5"/>
                     <l> He did from Earth to Heaven go,</l>
                     <l>When he had finish'd here by Death.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.30.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For sure such claim and interest</l>
                     <l>Each Spouse to her true Love may lay,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That where his presence may be best</l>
                     <l>For her, that there he'd 'bide and stay.</l>
                     <l>Methinks 'tis strange that such sweet things</l>
                     <l>Are held out to us in his Book,</l>
                     <l>That as his Heirs, and Sons, and Kings,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Unto himself he hath us took:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And yet we droop as if that he</l>
                     <l>For our poor Souls had nothing done;</l>
                     <l>And that all was a phantasie,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.31</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Both Promise, Truth, and Book, and Son.</l>
                     <l>Christ hath declar'd he is our Friend,</l>
                     <l>Our Father, Brother, Flesh and Bone;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our Head, and our Companion kind;</l>
                     <l>And that we are not two, but one.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That his own flesh is not more dear</l>
                     <l>To him, than we poor Sinners are:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.29.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Why then should we be sad or fear,</l>
                     <l>Since he for his doth take such care?</l>
                     <l>All pow'r in Heav'n and in Earth too,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is his that us doth love so dear;</l>
                     <l>All good things he therefore will do</l>
                     <l>For us, we need it not to fear.</l>
                     <l>And what may truly hurtful be</l>
                     <l>To any that he thus doth love,</l>
                     <l>Be sure he cann't endure to see,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But it from us he will remove.</l>
                     <l>And therefore (Love) we quite mistake</l>
                     <l>When we do think that he doth ought</l>
                     <l>That doth against true comfort make,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.45.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Since he our Comforts dearly bought.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:152495:6"/>
                     <l> Or when we think that he intends</l>
                     <l>By those things which we judge are bad,</l>
                     <l>To press our Hearts when he them sends,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And make our Minds and Spirits sad:</l>
                     <l>No, no; there's no such bitter thought</l>
                     <l>Dwells in his sweet and golden Heart,</l>
                     <l>To those that he so dearly bought,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.55, 56.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For whom he felt Death's deadly smart.</l>
                     <l>And why? Because such bitter things,</l>
                     <l>Through Grace, like Pills, do purge away</l>
                     <l>The humours ill,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 27.9. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.12.</note> and soundness brings;</l>
                     <l>Therefore on us he doth them lay.</l>
                     <l>And why? Because these things do tend,</l>
                     <l>As the right means, to bring about</l>
                     <l>True Comforts in the latter end:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.20. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To his in love he sends them out.</l>
                     <l>And if this truth was in our Eye</l>
                     <l>Always in view, when sad things come;</l>
                     <l>An Heav'n in Hell we should descry,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.35. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And joy in what was erst our doom.</l>
                     <l>Yea, surely <hi>(Love)</hi> we glad should be</l>
                     <l>In all sad things that us befall;</l>
                     <l>In Peril,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.25, 26.</note> Sword, the cursed Tree,</l>
                     <l>Distress, Death, Famine; yea, in all:</l>
                     <l>In Nakedness, Thirst, Hunger, Cold,</l>
                     <l>Stripes, Prisons, Wants, &amp; loss of Friends;</l>
                     <l>In spoil of Goods,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.25. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.</note> in manifold</l>
                     <l>Temptations; for good all tends.</l>
                     <l>And surely <hi>(Love)</hi> in all these things</l>
                     <l>We more are now,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17.</note> than Conquerours,</l>
                     <l>Through him that lov'd us, and as Kings</l>
                     <l>And Priests hath made us; yea, his Heirs.</l>
                     <l>We should rejoyce, and joy again;</l>
                     <l>Yea,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Philip</hi> 4.4.</note> we should evermore rejoyce,</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152495:6"/>
                     <l> Whate'er befalls, and sing amain;</l>
                     <l>Yea, and advance our singing Voice.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 68.3, 4 <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.39.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>What nothing hurt! Nor nothing lose!</l>
                     <l>Nor nothing that can do us wrong!</l>
                     <l>And yet that we should droop like those</l>
                     <l>That never learn'd that sweet new Song!<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>What, all things now, both good and bad,</l>
                     <l>All working for our greatest gain!<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And yet that we should still be sad,</l>
                     <l>And from our sighing not refrain!<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 45.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fie, fie, for shame! We God displease,</l>
                     <l>That for us all this good hath done;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.47</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To take off smart, and give us ease,</l>
                     <l>That we with joy our Race might run.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 20.24.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And doubtless <hi>(Love)</hi> to this intent,</l>
                     <l>That we might live a life of Joy,</l>
                     <l>His Son into the world he sent,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74, 75.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To take away what might anoy.</l>
                     <l>And now if we do still remain</l>
                     <l>In sadness, and do droop in mind;</l>
                     <l>We make what he hath done in vain,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.1, 2, 3. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.13, 14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And shew ourselves to him unkind.</l>
                     <l>We many ways do him disgrace</l>
                     <l>Hereby, and strongly intimate,</l>
                     <l>And shew it in our very face,</l>
                     <l>That he does from his promise bate:</l>
                     <l>And that his love is not so true</l>
                     <l>As he pretends, nor pow'r so strong;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.27.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Since he doth suffer his to rue,</l>
                     <l>And many ways to suffer wrong.</l>
                     <l>That his Relations to us sweet,</l>
                     <l>Of Father, Husband, Friend, and Head,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>By which he often doth us greet,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 54.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are complements that are but dead.</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152495:7"/>
                     <l> And though these things on us do lay</l>
                     <l>A tye, and an engagement strong</l>
                     <l>Of love and tender care alway,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 103.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To our Relations, old and young;</l>
                     <l>To do them all the good we can,</l>
                     <l>And free them from all grief and care:</l>
                     <l>Yet these Relations a flim-flam</l>
                     <l>In God we count,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 49.14, 15.</note> and as the air.</l>
                     <l>Though we do attribute to him</l>
                     <l>Relations many, kind, and sweet;</l>
                     <l>Yet we deny the pow'r therein</l>
                     <l>Of love, that we must needs judge meet.</l>
                     <l>What fools are they that have a thought</l>
                     <l>That God, who made the Eye and Ear,</l>
                     <l>And both by wisdom rarely wrought,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 94.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That he should neither see nor hear?</l>
                     <l>Just so <hi>(my Dear)</hi> like Fools do we</l>
                     <l>Imagine in our carnal minds,</l>
                     <l>That God in us Affections free</l>
                     <l>Doth plant, to do what duty binds:</l>
                     <l>And yet himself such love doth want,</l>
                     <l>And care, that suits a Fathers mind;</l>
                     <l>And that his Bowels are more scant</l>
                     <l>Than all the Creatures in their kind.</l>
                     <l>O no, (my Love) there's no such thing,</l>
                     <l>He doth excel the Creatures all:</l>
                     <l>And as the Hen under her Wing,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>He doth his Children sweetly call.</l>
                     <l>To his Relations he's more full</l>
                     <l>Than all the Creatures made by him;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 49.14, 15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all their love ebbs low, and's dull,</l>
                     <l>But he with love is full to th' brim.<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'll fay no more: If this be true,</l>
                     <l>That I to thee <hi>(my Love)</hi> have told,</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:152495:7"/>
                     <l> There's nothing ought to make thee rue,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor trouble thee, <hi>my Heart of Gold.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let such as wicked Husbands have,</l>
                     <l>Or Wives, or Sons, like <hi>Absalon,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Mourn when they see them laid in Grave,</l>
                     <l>Because they judge them lost and gone.</l>
                     <l>Let Infidels and Pagans all,</l>
                     <l>When their poor Wives &amp; Husbands dye,</l>
                     <l>Fill their sad Hearts with Brine and Gall,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 4.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in their mourning, howl and cry.</l>
                     <l>Well may these mourn &amp; pierce their heart,</l>
                     <l>There is no help for these poor souls;</l>
                     <l>They have no faith to ease their smart:</l>
                     <l>But we so doing, should be fools.</l>
                     <l>Alas, these have not faith to see</l>
                     <l>That glorious blessed Hope within,</l>
                     <l>Of Life and Immortality;</l>
                     <l>Nor are they to our Jesus kin.</l>
                     <l>But let not us after this wise</l>
                     <l>Mourn, when we lose our <hi>Friends</hi> below;</l>
                     <l>But in a sweet and heav'nly guise,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.32.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>What Nature gives, on them bestow.</l>
                     <l>There is a mourning that's in date</l>
                     <l>With Saints, that Nature doth require;</l>
                     <l>But that is mild and moderate,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And sweetly mixt with Joy intire:</l>
                     <l>Which though it melts the tender heart</l>
                     <l>Of gracious Souls, yet is it free</l>
                     <l>From that heart-killing deadly smart</l>
                     <l>That in poor Worldlings we do see.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And this same Grief doth make the mind</l>
                     <l>More gracious, humble, sober, wise,</l>
                     <l>More just, good, faithful, tender, kind;</l>
                     <l>And in this <hi>Baca,</hi> Springs do rise.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 84.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:152495:8"/>
                     <l> This is the grief (my <hi>Love</hi>) that I</l>
                     <l>To thee allow, to mourn for him</l>
                     <l>Who from thy sight is gone on high,</l>
                     <l>And doth in pleasure's River swim.</l>
                     <l>Thus mourn, <hi>my Love,</hi> when thou dost please,</l>
                     <l>With those sweet silent joyful Tears;</l>
                     <l>If it thy tender heart may ease,</l>
                     <l>Or heal frail Nature's kind Disease.</l>
                     <l>This will not stop that bubling Spring</l>
                     <l>Which does within thy Belly rise;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 4.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor hinder thee that Song to fing,</l>
                     <l>That none can learn but Godly VVise.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay, this thy heart will sweeten more</l>
                     <l>With Grace, and set thy mind on fire,</l>
                     <l>From Earth to Heaven for to soar,</l>
                     <l>VVhere thou shalt have thy hearts desire.</l>
                     <l>And now, my <hi>Love,</hi> I should of thee</l>
                     <l>My leave take for a little while,</l>
                     <l>Till we again each other see,</l>
                     <l>And on each other sweetly smile.</l>
                     <l>But onely that I have in mind</l>
                     <l>Still more a word or two to say,</l>
                     <l>To thee, my <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Friend</hi> so kind:</l>
                     <l>I'd have thee work while it is day.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 9.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>This little time that's like a span,</l>
                     <l>Thy Christ (my <hi>Love</hi>) to thee doth lend,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 39.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy Loyns to gird up like a man,</l>
                     <l>To watch,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 12.35, 36.</note> and burning Lights to spend.</l>
                     <l>Gird up thy <hi>Loyns,</hi> thy <hi>Lamps</hi> now light,</l>
                     <l>And store up Oyl, and always watch,</l>
                     <l>Until the Bridegroom comes in sight,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.10, 13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>All Midnight-Sleepers for to catch;</l>
                     <l>And opens to the Virgins wise,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Door</hi> that lets into the <hi>Room,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:152495:8"/>
                     <l> That's pav'd with love in comely guise,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where they abide with the Bridegroom.</l>
                     <l>I say, my Love, and say again,</l>
                     <l>Take heed and pray, and always watch,</l>
                     <l>Whilst thou in flesh dost here remain,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.36.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lest the old Serpent should thee catch.</l>
                     <l>Thou know'st the World's a ticklish place,</l>
                     <l>As full of snares as it can hold;<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And we are weak without his Grace,</l>
                     <l>And like to <hi>Eve,</hi> are too too bold.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And when the Tempter subtilly</l>
                     <l>For us his Snares and Baits doth lay,</l>
                     <l>We taken are e'en by and by,</l>
                     <l>And from him cannot turn away.</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Lusts</hi> within like <hi>Tinder</hi> be,</l>
                     <l>And his <hi>Temptations</hi> like a <hi>Spark;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No sooner <hi>touch,</hi> but <hi>take</hi> do we;</l>
                     <l>And if he <hi>shoots,</hi> he <hi>hits</hi> the Mark.</l>
                     <l>Alas, my <hi>Love,</hi> how prone are we</l>
                     <l>To Vice, and Sin, and what is nought;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Unless by Grace upheld we be</l>
                     <l>From sin, by him who hath us bought.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Methinks I see there is no way</l>
                     <l>For us these things for to withstand,</l>
                     <l>If we don't always watch and pray;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.41.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And when we sink, catch him by th'hand.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>When we our frailty well do know,</l>
                     <l>The VVorlds Temptations manifold,</l>
                     <l>The Tempters craft and power also,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And who alone can us uphold:</l>
                     <l>And thereupon do always pray,</l>
                     <l>And lean upon his strength, and watch,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And on his VVord by faith do stay;</l>
                     <l>The Div'l may tempt, but cannot catch.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:152495:9"/>
                     <l> And whilst (my Love) this course we take,</l>
                     <l>We are within our Castle-wall;</l>
                     <l>That though he make our hearts to ake,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.31, 32.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>He cann't prevail to make us fall.</l>
                     <l>And therefore (Love) if thou dost heed</l>
                     <l>Wisely what I to thee have said,</l>
                     <l>To doubt of help thou shalt not need,</l>
                     <l>Nor of the Tempter be afraid.</l>
                     <l>But when we lean on our own strength,</l>
                     <l>Neglect to pray, and keep our guard,</l>
                     <l>And lie secure; the Div'l at length</l>
                     <l>Doth catch us by his Watch and Ward.</l>
                     <l>Thou know'st (my Love) 'twas <hi>Peter's</hi> Case,</l>
                     <l>When his own strength he did not doubt,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.33, 34.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor lean upon his Masters Grace,</l>
                     <l>The Tempter did him quickly rout.</l>
                     <l>I hope (my Love) what e'er befalls,</l>
                     <l>Still thy Foundation sure doth stand;</l>
                     <l>And God doth know those whom he calls,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.19.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let that foul <hi>Fiend</hi> do what he can.</l>
                     <l>Yet is it good still to be wise,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lest we, like fools, sit down by th'loss;</l>
                     <l>For if the Tempter us surprize,</l>
                     <l>We must come home by weeping-cross.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.75.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Again (my Love) whilst thou liv'st here,</l>
                     <l>Be alwayes carefull to do good;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Relieve the poor, their Hearts up cheer,</l>
                     <l>As Christ hath thine even by his Blood.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy Bread upon the Waters cast,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccles.</hi> 11.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And doubtless after many days</l>
                     <l>Thou shalt it find again at last,</l>
                     <l>Though it were sunk upon the Seas.</l>
                     <l>And do not let thy left hand know</l>
                     <l>What thy right hand hath wifely done;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.3, 4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152495:9"/>
                     <l> And thou shalt reap what thou dost sow,</l>
                     <l>Both here, and in the World to come.</l>
                     <l>And let thy carriage friendly be,</l>
                     <l>To Poor and Rich, to High and Low,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To Young and Old, to Bond and Free,</l>
                     <l>To Wise and Simple, Friend and Foe.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>An humble carriage is the best,</l>
                     <l>And that which God and man doth please;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4. <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.1. <hi>Prov.</hi> 25.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all men it offendeth least,</l>
                     <l>And wrath and anger doth appease.</l>
                     <l>Besides, it sweetly doth adorn</l>
                     <l>Our minds, and ways that we profess;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And stops the mouths of those that scorn,</l>
                     <l>That they, in stead of cursing, bless.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.15, 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Again, it wins the hearts of men</l>
                     <l>The ways of Christ for to embrace,</l>
                     <l>When wise and humble they see them</l>
                     <l>That in those ways do walk and trace.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Again (my Love) in God alone</l>
                     <l>Delight thy self, make him thy All;</l>
                     <l>And he thy hearts desires each one,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 37.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To thee shall give, ev'n at thy call.</l>
                     <l>And one thing more I shall commend</l>
                     <l>Unto thy trust and tender care;</l>
                     <l>My Children (Love) whom God did lend</l>
                     <l>As blessings from his mercy rare.</l>
                     <l>O in the nurture of the Lord</l>
                     <l>See thou (my Love) them up do bring;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And train them up in his good word,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That they may worship <hi>Sion</hi>'s King:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And their Creator learn to know</l>
                     <l>In time of youth, that golden day;</l>
                     <l>And fear and love his Name also,</l>
                     <l>And faithfully his Word obey.</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:152495:10"/>
                     <l> And truly (Love) I more desire</l>
                     <l>This one thing needful for them all,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.42. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Than all the Gold that's try'd in fire,</l>
                     <l>Or Treasures on the earthen Ball.</l>
                     <l>If Christ,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal</hi> 144.15 <hi>Psal.</hi> 16.5, 6</note> my Love, their Portion be,</l>
                     <l>I know the Lines to them will fall</l>
                     <l>In pleasant Ground, and they shall see</l>
                     <l>That they shall never sink nor fall.</l>
                     <l>O pray (Dear Heart) and often pray</l>
                     <l>Unto thy God, as I have done,</l>
                     <l>That they may all his Voice obey,</l>
                     <l>And in his Ways their Race may run.</l>
                     <l>That we again with them may meet</l>
                     <l>In New <hi>Jerusalem,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.3.</note> and walk</l>
                     <l>All hand in hand,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.21.</note> i'th' Golden Street,</l>
                     <l>And of our Fathers Love may talk.</l>
                     <l>And in our Fathers Kingdom we,</l>
                     <l>With spotless Saints, and Angels bright,</l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Fathers</hi> face may always see,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>In Glory and eternal Light:</l>
                     <l>Where we shall also then behold</l>
                     <l>Our sweet Redeemers comely face,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>In Beauty far excelling Gold,</l>
                     <l>And richly deck'd with heav'nly Grace.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13, 14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in his Arms shall folded be,</l>
                     <l>And fill'd with Joy up to the brim;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 16.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where we no more shall sorrow see,</l>
                     <l>But in sweet Pleasures River swim.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>"Vers.</hi> 8.</note>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Farewel (my Love) I now must sleep;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Though more at parting I should say;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But parting words may strike too deep:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And therefore down my Pen I'll lay.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:10"/>
                  <p>A Spiritual Portion OF HEAVENLY TREASURE, Bequeathed By Mr. WILLIAM WHEELER, Late Minister of the Gospel, and Pastor of a Church of Christ at <hi>Cranfield</hi> in <hi>Bedfordshire;</hi> AS HIS Last Legacy TO HIS CHILDREN.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the year 1670.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:11"/>
                  <head>The EPISTLE.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My dear Children:</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HAving little of this Worlds Goods to leave with you after my decease, I thought it my duty to leave to each of you a small Portion or Legacy of such Treasure as the Lord hath bestowed on me: So that I may truly say in this Case, (as <hi>Peter</hi> once) <hi>Silver and Gold have I little; yet such as I have, give I unto you,</hi> And I humbly bow my knee to the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ, That together with it, be would give his Blessing.</p>
                  <p>And as for my writing this little Piece of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sel to you in this kind of Language, which possibly some may except against; take this account: I ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a little spare time from my more serious Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, took my Pen, and began to write a Verse or two, as it were in jest, and by way of Recreation, (though I had seldom or never formerly wrote any thing in that way.) And as I was writing, I found God, as I thought, very present with me, and my spirit on a sudden made very serious, and deeply en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in that thing which at first I so carelesly took in hand: So that now I had a greater work lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, than I was at all aware of when I first be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; neither could I at all decline from it, till I had perfectly waded through the same.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:12"/>
                  <p> Now before I had fully ended what I was about, a sense of Death began somewhat strongly to seiz upon my heart; and withal, this was impressed upon me, That it might be very good and necessary, that I should write something by way of Instruction and Counsel, to leave both with your Mother and you. And as I had found the presence of God in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and way of writing before, so now again I found my spirit most inclinable to go on in the same, in this little piece of my Advice and Counsel unto you; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I confess for want of practice I was very raw and unskilful in it.</p>
                  <p>Again, pon farther consideration, I thought also that the matter herein contained, would stick and dwell the better upon your minds; Verse being always a friend to weak Memories.</p>
                  <p>And lastly, I thought of the president (in the Book of Acts and Monuments) of that blessed Martyr <hi>Robert Smith,</hi> who wrote his godly Instructions to his Wife and Children in this way; which you may also read at your leisure.</p>
                  <p>And thus (my Children) I have given you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count both of my ends and inducements of writing this to you, as also of the mannner and way wherein I have done it: Which I the rather thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to do, both that the matter it self might be the more seriously weighed by you; as also, that if any dissatisfied spirit should, by any Providence, come to read the same, they may hereby be induced to look a little, before they leap; and weigh the Case, before they pass Sentence.</p>
                  <p>I have yet another word, which is this: If you should shew this little Piece to some, they may perhaps tell you, I have been too too sharp against the
<pb facs="tcp:152495:12"/>Ministry, and that I have chalk'd you out a very narrow path in that respect to walk in. But for that, I here tell both you and them, that I know not where to abate a tittle of what I have spoken: For the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and corrupt Ministry (which especially I have here aimed at, and cautioned you against) are I am confident the very Pest of this poor Nation, and the great Obstructors of the Gospel of Christ, and those that murther thousands of poor Souls amongst us; and how can I then with the discharge of my duty to God and you, say less than I have said?</p>
                  <p>My Children, It is not the advancing the way of <hi>Independancy,</hi> nor the debasing the way of <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> (as some possibly may think) that I contend so much for; though I do judge (as you may well perceive in this little Discourse) the latter in some particulars to be much more faulty and discrepant from the Rule, than the former; especially in the way of constituting Churches, and in Church-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and in the business of their pretended Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, with other like things: Yet I say again, it is not these things that lie with so much weight up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Spirit; but it is this carnal and dead Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry; because they are a company of blind Guides, as our Saviour calls them: and indeed, the very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Gospel, and all good; that neither (as he saith) <hi>enter into the Kingdom of God them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, nor suffer those that are entring.</hi> And had I but as able a Pen as some men have, I think I should lay them open to the Worlds view, a little more than yet I have done; that all might see, if God would, the great danger that their poor Souls lie in, whilst they sit down and content themselves under their Ministry.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:13"/>
                  <p> Yet (my Children) whilst I thus speak, I would not have you think that I judge all the carnal Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stry to lie onely amongst those of the National Way: No, no; there indeed I believe lieth the greatest bulk of them, though there be here and there a good man amongst them: But yet there are doubtless some carnal Ministers and Preachers, that want the Spirit of Christ, and the lively Word, even amongst those that are called Independants, and amongst all other distinct ways of Profession. <hi>There be Jades of all colours,</hi> if I may use that proverbial expression. And truly I must give you the same Counsel concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the one, as the other; that is, to take heed how you commit your immortal Souls to the trust and care of either of them.</p>
                  <p>For (my dear Children) 'tis the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and the sweet anointing of the Spirit of Grace, both in Ministers and Professors, that I would have you to prefer, before all Forms, Out-sides, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct Ways of Profession; as <hi>Episcopacy, Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, Independancy, Anabaptism,</hi> and such-like. And though it must needs be that some of these ways, in respect of the outside of Worship, are far worse, and more gross than the other; yet notwithstanding I would have you, if you meet with Ministers or Professors that are really Godly, and anointed with the holy Spirit, whether they be <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or <hi>Independants,</hi> to reverence them, love them, yea, and if their spirits be not too too bitter, to have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them so far as fairly you may or can. And though possibly you cannot own, nor go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them in their way in many things, because you see 'tis dark, antichristian, and erroneous, (God having not yet opened their Eyes, and enlightened
<pb facs="tcp:152495:13"/>them in these things) yet own the Men, own their Graces, own the anointing of Gods holy Spirit in them, and close with that; and take heed you do not, in disallowing that which is of man in them, disallow that which is of God also; as many, but yet foolishly and injudiciously, do.</p>
                  <p>O (my Children) I clearly see that two things in these our days are the confusion of all, and the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of all Rents and Distractions amongst the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of the Gospel:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>I.</hi> When men are so injudicious, that if they see others wrapt up in any piece of Antichristian Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, that then they think they are wholly Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, and so no kind of Christian Communion to be held with them. Alas for pity! Who is the man that can wash his hands, and say, <hi>I am clean?</hi> And if not, then by the same Rule, others that see them erre, may cast them off in like manner.</p>
                  <p>Again, I would fain ask these men this one Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, concerning those that are Godly, and yet lie in much Antichristian Darkness, as they judge, <hi>Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Christ Jesus hath Communion with such, or not?</hi> I suppose they cannot but say, Yea, in some measure he hath: Well then, I say who art thou that darest to cast off, and deny all Communion with them, that yet Christ himself hath Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with? I know indeed in case of evident scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, or offence given, the People of God both may and ought to withdraw, even from those that they judge Godly, and deny Communion with them for a time; us in that case, doubtless Christ himself doth no less. But I cannot yet believe that that case reacheth this, and that for these three Reasons:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Because 'tis evident to me, that many good
<pb facs="tcp:152495:14"/>men lie wrapt up in much Antichristian Darkness, not willfully, and being conscious to themselves of it, (as some doubtless are, whom God doth and will deal with accordingly) but because God hath not as yet opened their eyes, and enlightned them to see other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Because those scandalous offences are things evident, and openly manifest to all, and so cast a foul stain and reproach upon Religion, and so provoke the Lord to jealousie the more; but 'tis not altogether so here, because in many things Antichrist hath twisted and woven so fine a Web, that it is hardly discerna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the best of Saints; at least in these days, that are neither dark nor light, as the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> speaks, <hi>Zach. 14.6, 7.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Because I clearly see that Christ doth not charge these kind of errors or mistakes so high, at least upon such who are not wilfully blind, and that do not even shut their eyes against the Light, (as I believe some do) as he doth in the other case of evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and open scandal; by withdrawing his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and suspending his Spirit of Grace from them. And therefore let us take heed that we do not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw farther than Christ himself doth: But as we have a general Rule, That Believers in Church-Communion should onely separate from Unbelievers, and the Seed of the Woman from the Seed of the Serpent; so let us see to it, that we keep within our bounds: For truly (let me tell you my thoughts) to withdraw all Christian Communion from those men that we have sometimes judged godly, before we see that God hath utterly withdrawn his presence, and before the Spirit of Grace hath quite done breathing in them; seems to me, just as if we should leave men
<pb facs="tcp:152495:14"/>and bury them, before the breath is out of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; and therefore as we commonly are careful not utterly to leave men, before their breath is gone; so let us do in this Case: Except onely when either their Spirits are so bitter and invective, that they cannot be born; or else in some eminently contagious spiritual Disease, which may be well compared to the Pox or Plague; and in such Cases I think a with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from them is not amiss.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>II.</hi> Again, There is another thing which (as I said) confounds all, and that is this; when men do out of a blind preposterous Zeal, prefer the out-side of Worship and Religion, before the inside and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it; which we may clearly see in some men: for when they have found out, as they think, a more right way of Worship than others; they presently fall a judging and censuring all that are not in their way, as ignorant, low, and short of themselves; whereas (though it should be even so, in respect of the out-side of Worship, yet possibly) those that are so censured may have five times more of the power and life of Religion and Godliness in them, than those that censure: And the reason is, Because God doth not reveal all parts of his Mind and Worship to his People at once; but makes plain some things to one, and some to another, even as he sees cause; that so all, when they come to see their mistakes and short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, might see that they are but men, and have need of the help and advice of their Brethren, even as the Members in the natural Body have one of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: That so they might hereby be driven to walk hunsbly with God, and tenderly one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:15"/>
                  <p> These things, my dear Children, I thought good a little to bint out to you; lest (whilst you endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to follow my Counsel) to avoid one Extream, you should run your selves into another, as too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny do.</p>
                  <p>I have now done: The Lord, who I hope hath been my <hi>GOD</hi> hitherto, bless you abundantly, and give you plentifully of his <hi>Grace</hi> and Spirit, and the knowledge of his dear Son in your hearts; and bless the reading of this little Piece to you.</p>
                  <p>Farewel in the Lord.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your dear Father,</hi> William Wheeler.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152495:15"/>
                  <head>A Spiritual Portion OF Heavenly TREASURE. OR, The Last Legacy of Mr. <hi>William Wheeler,</hi> to his Children.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>ATtend, attend, my Children all,</l>
                     <l>Unto your Fathers Counsel grave,</l>
                     <l>And listen unto Wisdom's Call,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.20.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whereby she seeks your Souls to save.</l>
                     <l>Dear Babes, your <hi>Father</hi> thought it meet,</l>
                     <l>Before he left the World below,</l>
                     <l>On you (to him so dear and sweet)</l>
                     <l>This Paper-Present to bestow.</l>
                     <l>That you might clearly read and see</l>
                     <l>What once within his heart did dwell;</l>
                     <l>And taste what frame of Spirit he</l>
                     <l>Was of, for you; these Lines do tell.</l>
                     <l>Whilst I did live in perfect health,</l>
                     <l>A sense of death, I know not how,</l>
                     <l>Did on me seiz, as 'twere by stealth,</l>
                     <l>Which made my stubborn heart soon bow.</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:152495:16"/>
                     <l> Methought the Lord me warning give,</l>
                     <l>To be preparing for my Change;</l>
                     <l>That Death might no advantage have,</l>
                     <l>Nor I to think his coming strange.</l>
                     <l>Now what effect this Instinct had</l>
                     <l>Upon my heart, I here shall shew:</l>
                     <l>It made me fearful, and yet glad,</l>
                     <l>That to my end so near I grew.</l>
                     <l>Fearful I was, because I knew</l>
                     <l>What deadness, and a barren heart,</l>
                     <l>Had late possest me; and in view</l>
                     <l>A world of baseness up did start,</l>
                     <l>But glad I was, because I thought</l>
                     <l>That God in love did warning give</l>
                     <l>To me, to do what long I sought,</l>
                     <l>Namely, more like a Saint to live.</l>
                     <l>I thought this warning sweet would make</l>
                     <l>Me far more careful than before,</l>
                     <l>And from vain things my heart off take,</l>
                     <l>And make my mind to Heaven soar.</l>
                     <l>Thus did these Twins together strive</l>
                     <l>Within my heart a little space,</l>
                     <l>As if they had been things alive,</l>
                     <l>Lab'ring each other to displace.</l>
                     <l>But presently I did resolve,</l>
                     <l>Through Grace, these few things for to do,</l>
                     <l>Before Death should me quite dissolve,</l>
                     <l>And I this world should quite forgo.</l>
                     <l>My house in order first to set,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all things leave in such a frame,</l>
                     <l>That nothing might disturb or let</l>
                     <l>Me at my parting, to my blame.</l>
                     <l>And secondly, I thought it meet</l>
                     <l>Some good Instructions to leave</l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:152495:16"/>
                     <l> With you, and with your Mother sweet,</l>
                     <l>When you of me Death should bereave.</l>
                     <l>Which I, according to my skill,</l>
                     <l>In two small Paper-Books have done:</l>
                     <l>Pray for the Deed, accept the Will;</l>
                     <l>When over them your Eye doth run.</l>
                     <l>And see that you to heart do lay,</l>
                     <l>What good Advice to you I give;</l>
                     <l>Don't dare with dying words to play,</l>
                     <l>But learn by them how you may live.</l>
                     <l>Thirdly, Upon my heart imprest</l>
                     <l>A strong desire there was, that I</l>
                     <l>Might spend my little time to th' best,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15, 16. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.2, 3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Before I in the Grave should lie,</l>
                     <l>That now redeem at last I might</l>
                     <l>My many mispent-hours, and lay</l>
                     <l>My Strength and Talents out for Christ,</l>
                     <l>And give my self him to obey.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.15. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That now I might do good to all,</l>
                     <l>And glory to Gods Name might bring,</l>
                     <l>And many Souls from darkness call,</l>
                     <l>To worship their eternal King.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 26.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Much griev'd was I, ev'n to the heart,</l>
                     <l>To think that I much time had lost;</l>
                     <l>This was my wound and bitter smart,</l>
                     <l>And many sighs this did me cost.</l>
                     <l>And lastly, this did make me pray,</l>
                     <l>And pray again unto the Lord;</l>
                     <l>That he my suit would not gainsay,</l>
                     <l>But some more time to me afford;</l>
                     <l>Wherein I might have time and space,</l>
                     <l>My strength, with <hi>David,</hi> to restore;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 39.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Before I should depart from hence,</l>
                     <l>And on the earth be seen no more.</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:152495:17"/>
                     <l> And like to that same gracious King,</l>
                     <l>Who turn'd himself unto the Wall,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 20.2, 3</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>His chattering plaints all forth to bring,</l>
                     <l>And for more time to God did call.</l>
                     <l>Ev'n so did I, when as I thought</l>
                     <l>How much work still I had to do;</l>
                     <l>His love to answer,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15.</note> which had bought</l>
                     <l>My Soul from Death, Hell, Wrath, &amp; <hi>Wo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Life for it self I did not crave,</l>
                     <l>But time to do my Father's will;</l>
                     <l>'Cause none can praise him in the Grave;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Isa.</hi> 38.19.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Living they may praise him still.</l>
                     <l>And thus you see what use I made</l>
                     <l>Of what suggested was to me,</l>
                     <l>Before my time away did fade,</l>
                     <l>And I among the Dead was free.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 88.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And now, my Babes, my speech to you</l>
                     <l>Directed is; I pray give Ear;</l>
                     <l>And what you hear, that strive to do,</l>
                     <l>VVith rev'rence and with godly fear.</l>
                     <l>First let me tell you, That in sin</l>
                     <l>You all are dead,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.1.</note> and in the Grave;</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Adam</hi>'s Children all have bin:</l>
                     <l>And none but Christ your Souls can save.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 4.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea, though your Parents Godly were,</l>
                     <l>A mercy great, because that they</l>
                     <l>Their Children teach the Lord to fear,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.4. <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.19.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Keep his commands; and for them pray.</l>
                     <l>Yet still unless <hi>Jehovah</hi> do</l>
                     <l>Bless their Endeavours by his Grace,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And work a change in your hearts too,</l>
                     <l>You still are of the Serpents Race.</l>
                     <l>'Tis not enough for you to say,</l>
                     <l>That you are all of <hi>Abram</hi>'s seed;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152495:17"/>
                     <l> Unless you shall his Voice obey,</l>
                     <l>And bring forth fruit that's good indeed.</l>
                     <l>What though in such an Age you live,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 11.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wherein the Gospel-Sun shines clear?</l>
                     <l>Yet if the Lord Light do not give</l>
                     <l>Into your hearts, you're ne'er near.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>What though you live that Age to see,</l>
                     <l>Wherein Christs Kingdom high shall rise,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 9.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And millions of sweet Saints shall be,</l>
                     <l>And few that dare the same despise?<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezek.</hi> 28.24.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet if the Sun of Righteousness</l>
                     <l>Don't rise, with healing Wings,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2.</note> upon</l>
                     <l>Your Souls, the same with Grace to bless,</l>
                     <l>You perish, and are still undone.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 12.35.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O nothing but that Change alone,</l>
                     <l>That all things new within doth make,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. <hi>John</hi> 15.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And you and Christ unites in one,</l>
                     <l>Can save you from th' infernal Lake,</l>
                     <l>And yet this Change, I must you tell,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 13.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Not you, nor Saints, nor Angels all,</l>
                     <l>Nor all the Dead, if brought from Hell,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.31.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can work, if his Great Voice don't call.</l>
                     <l>But you will say, <hi>What shall we do,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If thus the case with us doth stand?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hark, and I will declare to you;</l>
                     <l>And you shall hear the matter scan'd.</l>
                     <l>Though God, and all his People, know</l>
                     <l>This work cannot be wrought by man;</l>
                     <l>Yet God directs us what to do;</l>
                     <l>Namely, at Wisdom's Gates to stand.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.34.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And when she calls and cries i'th' streets,</l>
                     <l>Or open Gates,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.20, 21.</note> or in the place</l>
                     <l>Of concourse, and the simple greets,</l>
                     <l>With sweet Reproof; then her embrace.</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:152495:18"/>
                     <l> When she doth cry,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22.</note> amidst the throng,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ye simple ones that me despise:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And to you saith, <hi>How long, how long,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>How long will't be ere you be wise?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If you at my Reproof will turn,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Spirit I will pour on you;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which in your hearts like fire shall burn,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And help and teach you what to do.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>There is a time (my Children dear).<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 64.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhen you the Means of Grace attend,</l>
                     <l>That Christ (this <hi>Wisdom</hi>) will come near,</l>
                     <l>And to your hearts his Spirit send.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.20.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And that shall rap, and bounce, and knock,</l>
                     <l>At Conscience-Door;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.20.</note> and shall awake</l>
                     <l>The sleepy Soul, now like a Block,</l>
                     <l>And make poor guilty Conscience quake.</l>
                     <l>This is your time; O fear not now</l>
                     <l>To open wide to him the Door;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 24.7, 9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For he your stubborn hearts will bow,</l>
                     <l>And will convince you more and more.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23. <hi>John</hi> 16.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And make you know your selves and sin,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Death</hi> &amp; <hi>Wrath,</hi> the <hi>Curse, &amp; Hell;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And what a woful case you're in,</l>
                     <l>And how the Dev'l doth in you dwell.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.2.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And how you are quite gone astray</l>
                     <l>From him,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 53.6. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.12.</note> like all the world beside;</l>
                     <l>That all are turn'd out of the way,</l>
                     <l>And all have left their God and Guide.</l>
                     <l>And of his glory short do fall,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Involved wholly under sin;</l>
                     <l>And in gross darkness lying all,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fast bound and snar'd in Satan's gin.</l>
                     <l>Now when he thus doth call and knock,</l>
                     <l>I know that you afraid will be,</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:152495:18"/>
                     <l> The Door to open and unlock,</l>
                     <l>Lest he your guilty hearts should see,</l>
                     <l>You will be like that naked man</l>
                     <l>Whom in the Garden God did call,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And hide your selves, if that you can,</l>
                     <l>That find you he might not at all.</l>
                     <l>But do not so in any case;</l>
                     <l>Let me (my Babes) advise you here;</l>
                     <l>But let him in, and him embrace;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.2.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For you his entrance need not fear.</l>
                     <l>'Tis true, as I already said,</l>
                     <l>Your selves and sins he'll make you see;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.20. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.36.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And at first sight you'll be afraid,</l>
                     <l>Although he comes to make you free.</l>
                     <l>O fear not; for assuredly,</l>
                     <l>The end of his approach is this,</l>
                     <l>By sight of sin,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.24. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.21. 1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.10.</note> to make you fly</l>
                     <l>Unto your Christ, who will you kiss;</l>
                     <l>And save you from your selves and sins,</l>
                     <l>From Death, and from eternal Wrath;</l>
                     <l>And from the World, and Satan's gins;</l>
                     <l>And from your Foes ensnaring Path.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.34.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lo, this is so; I know it well;</l>
                     <l>And so do thousands more beside:</l>
                     <l>This is the end, we can you tell:</l>
                     <l>Ten thousand times hath this been tri'de.</l>
                     <l>O do not fear the Door to ope,</l>
                     <l>When his convincing Word doth knock;</l>
                     <l>Once more I tell you, 'Tis his scope</l>
                     <l>To build you upon that sure Rock.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.18. <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And after you convinc'd of sin</l>
                     <l>He hath, then soon of Righteousness</l>
                     <l>He to convince you will begin;</l>
                     <l>And then that happy day you'll bless.</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:152495:19"/>
                     <l> He'll shew you how he's satisfi'd</l>
                     <l>By Christs sweet death,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.12.</note> for all your sin,</l>
                     <l>As much as if your selves had dy'd</l>
                     <l>Upon the Cross, the Crown to win.</l>
                     <l>He'll make you see that 'tis all one,</l>
                     <l>That Christ his Law did once fulfil,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As if that you the same had done,</l>
                     <l>And perfectly had wrought his will.</l>
                     <l>And what your Christ for Sinners wrought,</l>
                     <l>He fully will impute to you;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And how you are compleatly bought,</l>
                     <l>Though nothing you your selves can do.</l>
                     <l>He'll shew you all that golden Chain,</l>
                     <l>How you Elect and Called are,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.30.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And Justifi'd; with all the Train</l>
                     <l>That follows from his mercy rare.</l>
                     <l>And furthermore, I this can say,</l>
                     <l>If when he knocks, you ope the Door;</l>
                     <l>Then he will come in,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.23.</note> day by day,</l>
                     <l>To help and teach you more and more.</l>
                     <l>But if,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 3.20.</note> because your deeds are nought,</l>
                     <l>This blessed Light you strive to fly;</l>
                     <l>Though your great good it always sought,</l>
                     <l>At last this Guide away will hie.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>It will not always call and knock,</l>
                     <l>Though to depart seem loth it do;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hebr.</hi> 3.7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet 'twill be gone, if long you mock,</l>
                     <l>And scarce return,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.13, 14.</note> tho much sought to.</l>
                     <l>Yet this I say to such as shall</l>
                     <l>Out-stand the knockings of this Guess,</l>
                     <l>And after see their madness all,</l>
                     <l>And heartily themselves address,</l>
                     <l>To seek him with their hearts again;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Judg.</hi> 10.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>He will to them return at last,</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152495:19"/>
                     <l> And pour in melting Grace amain,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Forgetting all that's gon and past.</l>
                     <l>Yet O take heed; I tell you plain,</l>
                     <l>That sacred things will 'bide no jest;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And many hearts full low have lain</l>
                     <l>For this, as they have oft confest.</l>
                     <l>And truly this I more shall say,</l>
                     <l>Gods secret purpose to pass by,</l>
                     <l>This knowing of our time and day,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.42.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is that wherein our Life doth lie.</l>
                     <l>And 'tis our death, this not to know;</l>
                     <l>Our Habitation desolate</l>
                     <l>It makes, and us it lays full low;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.38.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of Hell this opens wide the Gate.</l>
                     <l>This is the condemnation just,</l>
                     <l>That in the World Life doth appear;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 3.20.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But men to keep their filthy lust,</l>
                     <l>Love darkness, but the light they fear.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore, because I call'd,</hi> (saith he)</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And to my Voice you gave no ear;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.23, 24, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So you, in your Calamity,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall call to me, but I'll not hear.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Again (dear Hearts) as I you told</l>
                     <l>In what sad state your Souls do lie;</l>
                     <l>How under Sin and Satan sold</l>
                     <l>You are, and what means to apply:</l>
                     <l>How you at Wisdom's Gates should tend,</l>
                     <l>And wait upon the means of grace;</l>
                     <l>And when he doth the Spirit send</l>
                     <l>To knock, that then you it embrace.</l>
                     <l>So now again, declare I shall,</l>
                     <l>What I by Wisdom's Gates intend;</l>
                     <l>And what the means of grace I call,</l>
                     <l>To which your ear I'd have you lend.</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152495:20"/>
                     <l> That preaching of the Word, say I,</l>
                     <l>In which a gracious Spirit runs;</l>
                     <l>Therein the means of Grace doth lie;</l>
                     <l>Such Preachers are Anointed Ones.<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 2.27. <hi>John</hi> 3.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Such as do preach what they do know,</l>
                     <l>And testifie what they have seen;</l>
                     <l>These to poor Souls much good will do,</l>
                     <l>Their word is like a Svord that's keen.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>There is a preaching that's but Chaff,</l>
                     <l>As God himself the same accounts;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.28.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis nothing else but meer Riff-Raff;</l>
                     <l>It to good hearts no more amounts.</l>
                     <l>And all such Preachers strangers are</l>
                     <l>To God,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 10 5.</note> and to all good men too;</l>
                     <l>And for mens Souls they do not care,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.2, 3, 4. <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And them to save, they nothing do.</l>
                     <l>These men did never eat the Book</l>
                     <l>That makes the Preachers Belly sowre;</l>
                     <l>These like Anointed Ones don't look;</l>
                     <l>Nor have they to do good the pow'r.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.32. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34.3, 19.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But feed themselves, and starve the Flock,</l>
                     <l>And water muddy, and make foul;</l>
                     <l>They never drank into the Rock;</l>
                     <l>But blind they are as any Owl.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 42.19.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And these may preach till Doomsday come,</l>
                     <l>And scarcely save one simple Soul;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.32. <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But blind-fold all, and harden some,</l>
                     <l>That on they'l go, without controul.</l>
                     <l>The reason is,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.17.</note> their Arm's dry'd up,</l>
                     <l>And their right Eye God dark hath made;</l>
                     <l>For drinking of that golden Cup,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And making of his Work a Trade.</l>
                     <l>'Tis true, some Truths these men dispence,</l>
                     <l>And do the same in words declare;</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:152495:20"/>
                     <l> But not i'th' Spirits evidence,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.4</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As by good men held forth they are.</l>
                     <l>And hence they want that Majesty,</l>
                     <l>That melting and convincing pow'r,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mich.</hi> 5.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That doth in all true Preaching lie,</l>
                     <l>To shake the heart, that Rocky Tow'r.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 2 25.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>They speak not by that living Voice,</l>
                     <l>That makes the Dead to hear and live;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 5.25.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Christs sheep to hear them can't rejoyce;</l>
                     <l>Strange sounds to them their Voice doth give.</l>
                     <l>There is no savour in their word,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 10.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That gracious Souls can taste or find;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And at sometimes 'tis like a </l>
                     <l>And nauseous to a gracious mind.</l>
                     <l>I know right well there is a Crew</l>
                     <l>Of beastly Priests, who if they hear</l>
                     <l>What I have said, though 'tis all true,</l>
                     <l>Yet will they proudly scoff and jear.</l>
                     <l>But I don't care; for this I'm sure,</l>
                     <l>Th' Eternal God will them disown;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their Kingdom will not long indure,</l>
                     <l>They shall in wrath be overthrown.</l>
                     <l>The time will come, when as you shall</l>
                     <l>The voice of Shepherds howling hear;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their glory spoild, and down they fall;</l>
                     <l>And at their fall, some quake for fear.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>My scope is not you to deter</l>
                     <l>From hearing any godly man;</l>
                     <l>Dissenter though, or Presbyter,</l>
                     <l>That faithfully doth what he can:</l>
                     <l>And hath Gods holy Spirit, to</l>
                     <l>Assist in what he undertakes;</l>
                     <l>Although he be not so and so,</l>
                     <l>As some men be, whom God so makes.</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:152495:21"/>
                     <l> I do not like that Spirit in some,</l>
                     <l>That none but their own Tribe will hear,</l>
                     <l>Though ne'er so gracious,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2.</note> and come home</l>
                     <l>Unto good hearts, and them up chear.</l>
                     <l>These seem to me, just like to <hi>John,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who vainly those good men forbid</l>
                     <l>To cast out Dev'ls, that had begun,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mark</hi> 9.38.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cause not with them they follow did.</l>
                     <l>Nor do I say, That we may not</l>
                     <l>At all a carnal Preacher hear,</l>
                     <l>When opportunely 'tis our lot</l>
                     <l>Where they are preaching, to come near.</l>
                     <l>For of my Conscience 'tis the state,</l>
                     <l>Not to abridge mens liberty;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.29.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Though such are almost out of date,</l>
                     <l>Yet good we may receive thereby.</l>
                     <l>For first, we see the difference</l>
                     <l>Betwixt these dead men, and all those</l>
                     <l>That do the lively Word dispence,</l>
                     <l>Whom for that work the Lord hath chose.</l>
                     <l>Besides, we may their spirits taste,</l>
                     <l>How light,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.32.</note> how flat, frothy and low;</l>
                     <l>And how to leave them God makes haste,</l>
                     <l>Them and their works to overthrow.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.8, 9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Again, neither dire I deny</l>
                     <l>But God to us the Word may bless,</l>
                     <l>Whoever it be held forth by;</l>
                     <l>Though 'tis but seldom I confess.</l>
                     <l>Yet on the other side, I say,</l>
                     <l>Our selves we ought not to content,</l>
                     <l>That we have heard such preach and pray;</l>
                     <l>Because these run,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.32.</note> and are not sent.</l>
                     <l>And therefore, though sometimes we may,</l>
                     <l>On such accounts as I have shown,</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152495:21"/>
                     <l> Hear what these men do preach and say;</l>
                     <l>Yet still do not them so far own,</l>
                     <l>As under them for to sit down,</l>
                     <l>And to commit unto their care</l>
                     <l>Our precious Souls, though most i'th' Town</l>
                     <l>Perhaps may do't; yet don't you dare.</l>
                     <l>For God these men doth seldom bless,</l>
                     <l>But to themselves he doth them leave,</l>
                     <l>That what they do is still fruitless;</l>
                     <l>Samll good by them you can receive.</l>
                     <l>Therefore as God doth leave these men,</l>
                     <l>Even so (dear Babes) leave you them too.</l>
                     <l>I mean in frequent hearing them;</l>
                     <l>O trust them not; they'l you undo.</l>
                     <l>I don't in malice speak these things;</l>
                     <l>Both they and I shall one day stand</l>
                     <l>Before the Judge, the King of Kings,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Where I believe this shall be scan'd.</l>
                     <l>And I believe I shall not blush</l>
                     <l>To think what I against them said,</l>
                     <l>Before that God that dwelt i'th' bush;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor for this Censure be afraid.</l>
                     <l>I well do know I frailties have,</l>
                     <l>At which I often blush to think;</l>
                     <l>From them the Lord me wash and save:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psa.</hi> 51.2, 7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet at these men I cannot wink.</l>
                     <l>Because they Lanthorns dark have been,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To lead poor simple Souls to Hell;</l>
                     <l>They under them the Light han't seen,</l>
                     <l>But all their Life in darkness dwell.</l>
                     <l>I know in this old Ministrie,</l>
                     <l>Which long time hath amongst us bin,</l>
                     <l>That here and there some good men be;</l>
                     <l>But truly they are very thin.</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:152495:22"/>
                     <l> And for these men, I love them well;</l>
                     <l>Though for their way, <hi>I</hi> judge them out;</l>
                     <l>And though in Gifts some do excell,</l>
                     <l>Yet in their way God will them rout.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> don't deny such good men are</l>
                     <l>The Ministers of Christ the Lord;</l>
                     <l>Them such their very Gifts declare,</l>
                     <l>When they do pray, or preach his Word.</l>
                     <l>But truly this I must them tell,</l>
                     <l>That in this point they are far wide;</l>
                     <l>For in their Fold the Goats do dwell,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And they profess to be their Guide.</l>
                     <l>This is the cause why at this day,</l>
                     <l>The Hurdles being now fell down,</l>
                     <l>That from these folds Sheep go away,</l>
                     <l>'Cause in them lie all Goats i'th' Town.</l>
                     <l>The Sheep do love in flocks to go,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And by themselves together feed,</l>
                     <l>And single out from Goats also,</l>
                     <l>Because they wear not their own weed.</l>
                     <l>Again, In this they're strangely out;</l>
                     <l>That some poor few of such as those,</l>
                     <l>Do joyn unto a cursed rout</l>
                     <l>Of carnal Priests, whom God ne'er chose;</l>
                     <l>But one intire thing up to make,</l>
                     <l>Namely, a Ministry for Christ,</l>
                     <l>And yet aside these few but take,</l>
                     <l>The rest from <hi>Babel</hi> took their rise:</l>
                     <l>At leastwise this to me is plain,</l>
                     <l>That they much rather do comply</l>
                     <l>With those that are of this same strain,</l>
                     <l>Than where's more grace and honesty.</l>
                     <l>I see full well what is the thing,</l>
                     <l>These men fain would their <hi>Babel</hi> heal,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152495:22"/>
                     <l> At such a time when <hi>Sion</hi>'s King</l>
                     <l>Will deadly Vengeance to her deal.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 51.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And truly it is dangerous</l>
                     <l>For all good men still so to do;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>God blasts their Gifts, their Counsels close</l>
                     <l>Blows up; they can't unplagued go.</l>
                     <l>These men, though good, yet still they stand</l>
                     <l>Upon the wrong side of that Cloud,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.20</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which is to lead God's Own by th' hand,</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Egypt</hi>'s Land, and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> proud.</l>
                     <l>And one thing I do much desire,</l>
                     <l>That all good men who see them erre</l>
                     <l>Thus grosly, out of love intire</l>
                     <l>To pray for them do not defer.</l>
                     <l>Some grudge, complain, and hardly speak</l>
                     <l>Of them, as there's some cause, no doubt,</l>
                     <l>But this won't do, not them off break;</l>
                     <l>'Tis God must put them to the rout.</l>
                     <l>And certainly much cause have we</l>
                     <l>To pity such, and for them pray;</l>
                     <l>Because Gods chosen ones they be,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And we may err as well as they.</l>
                     <l>And now I have declar'd to you</l>
                     <l>What is the wholesom means of Grace</l>
                     <l>That you should all give ear unto,</l>
                     <l>And with all diligence embrace.</l>
                     <l>That faithful preaching of his word,</l>
                     <l>Wherein a gracious Spirit runs,</l>
                     <l>Which sharper is than any Sword,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.12]</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And upside-down mens hearts it turns.</l>
                     <l>To which, if farther adde you shall,</l>
                     <l>The reading of the Scriptures too;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 5.39. <hi>Psal.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And Meditation in shall call,</l>
                     <l>And to good Christian Meetings go:</l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152495:23"/>
                     <l> This is the means that God ordains</l>
                     <l>That change within the heart to make,</l>
                     <l>And loose poor Souls from Satan's Chains,</l>
                     <l>And from their Necks them off to break.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal.</hi> 1.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O see that you this means attend;</l>
                     <l>And then sometimes you'l hear him knock;</l>
                     <l>At which time see your Ear you lend,</l>
                     <l>And do not that sweet Spirit mock:</l>
                     <l>For if you hearken, when he calls;</l>
                     <l>And him do follow,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.4.</note> when he draws;</l>
                     <l>That change within then find you shall,</l>
                     <l>And in your hearts he'll write his Laws.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.33.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And more and more will teach you still,</l>
                     <l>And help and lead you by the hand;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 25, 8, 9 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.27. <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.19. <hi>Isa.</hi> 7.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And will your hearts with comfort fill,</l>
                     <l>And bring you to that flowing Land.</l>
                     <l>He Butter will, and Honey too,</l>
                     <l>Cause you to eat, till know you shall</l>
                     <l>The good to chuse, and bad let go,</l>
                     <l>And him account your All in All.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Besides, his Beauty shining bright,</l>
                     <l>He'll make your inward Eyes behold;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 5.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your hearts to ravish with delight,</l>
                     <l>By Raptures sweet,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.5.</note> that can't be told.</l>
                     <l>Which will your hearts so deep engage</l>
                     <l>To him, with love, like flames of fire;</l>
                     <l>So hot,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.7.</note> much waters can't asswage</l>
                     <l>The heat thereof, 'tis so intire.</l>
                     <l>And when alive thus made are you,</l>
                     <l>And have received Eyes to see,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And hands to work, and feet to go,</l>
                     <l>And from the Grave are thus made free.</l>
                     <l>Then farther you I counsel give,</l>
                     <l>Like living men to work and act;</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152495:23"/>
                     <l> To strive like gracious Saints to live,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And of his Laws to keep the Tract.</l>
                     <l>For now in a capacity<note place="margin">1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.6, 7</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>You are, to work, and do Gods will;</l>
                     <l>Which whilst in darkness you did lie,</l>
                     <l>To do good works you had no skill.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For now the Children of the day</l>
                     <l>You are, now do the works of light;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Aside the works of darkness lay,</l>
                     <l>Because with you past is the night.</l>
                     <l>Now work whilst that your day doth last;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 9.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your time more precious is, than Gold:</l>
                     <l>Now to do good, see you make haste:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.58.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Time will not be for Rubies sold.</l>
                     <l>'Tis but a day that work you can;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 9.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>There is a night that soon will come:</l>
                     <l>Besides, this day's but like a span:</l>
                     <l>Work hard before night drives you home.</l>
                     <l>Now see that you Communion close<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 1.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>With God do keep; now watch and pray;</l>
                     <l>Now read his Book; with Saints discourse;</l>
                     <l>Now meditate both night and day.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 1.2. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.62.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now rise at Midnight him to praise,</l>
                     <l>For all his wondrous works of old,</l>
                     <l>And Judgements just, of latter days;</l>
                     <l>Which more have been, than can be told.</l>
                     <l>Now don't neglect one precious hour,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wherein you may the means of Grace</l>
                     <l>Enjoy, and feel therein the power<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of Christ, when you the same embrace.</l>
                     <l>Now call these days, days of delight;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 58.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And long till those sweet days do come,</l>
                     <l>That you appear may in his sight,</l>
                     <l>His gracious holy Saints among.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 84.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:152495:24"/>
                     <l> Where in is living Temple, you</l>
                     <l>May see the Beauty of his face,</l>
                     <l>And how your God and King doth go,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 68.24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>A midst his Saints, with Princely grace.</l>
                     <l>Now take all opportunities</l>
                     <l>That God doth put into your hand,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.28.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>All good to do that in you lies,</l>
                     <l>And evil likewise to withstand.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now let your conversation be</l>
                     <l>Such as his Gospel may become;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now walk like Saints, that all may see</l>
                     <l>That you this World count not your home.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.14. <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>You are the Light, you are the Salt</l>
                     <l>And savour of this World below;</l>
                     <l>So walk that none may see you halt,</l>
                     <l>But in a heavenly gesture go.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be holy now, and harmless too,</l>
                     <l>The Sons of God without all blame,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Before a crooked Nation, who</l>
                     <l>Do watch to scandalize your name.</l>
                     <l>Now let the savour of his Grace,</l>
                     <l>And of his Knowledge,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</note> by you be</l>
                     <l>Made manifest in ev'ry place,</l>
                     <l>That poor dark Souls the Light may see.</l>
                     <l>Now let those spangling Graces all</l>
                     <l>Shine forth in you,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.15.</note> which that sweet Dove</l>
                     <l>Into your hearts did once let fall,</l>
                     <l>True <hi>Patience, Meekness, Faith</hi> and <hi>Love;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>An humble heart wise and sincere,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 3.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sober, discreet, faithful and kind;</l>
                     <l>And bowels mixt with godly fear,</l>
                     <l>And what else suits an heav'nly mind.</l>
                     <l>In this good way see that you walk,</l>
                     <l>So soon as that true change is wrought;</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152495:24"/>
                     <l> But else in vain it is to talk,</l>
                     <l>To live like Saints, whom Christ hath bought.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 1.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>You surely will your selves deceive,</l>
                     <l>If that this change first be not laid</l>
                     <l>In the foundation, and bereave</l>
                     <l>Your selves of Comfort, as was said.</l>
                     <l>If that the Tree be good,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.18.</note> then will</l>
                     <l>The fruit it bears be good also;</l>
                     <l>But if the Tree's corrupt and ill,</l>
                     <l>Bad fruit on that same Tree will grow.</l>
                     <l>And if the fountain pute you see,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The streams as pure will from it slide;</l>
                     <l>But if the fountain muddy be,</l>
                     <l>The streams as muddy will abide.</l>
                     <l>But you may say, What should we do?</l>
                     <l>Should we not strive like Saints to live,</l>
                     <l>Because we are not so and so;</l>
                     <l>Nor God this change don't to us give?</l>
                     <l>My Babes, you do not hear me say</l>
                     <l>One word against your living well;</l>
                     <l>No word I speak that tends that way;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.19.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>I dare not teach you to rebell.</l>
                     <l>But I the onely way declare,</l>
                     <l>How to this life you might attain;</l>
                     <l>And this (dear Babes) is my great care,</l>
                     <l>That now you might not strive in vain.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc></desc>
                           </gap>.3, 4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>I shew you how begin you should</l>
                     <l>To take your work at the right end;</l>
                     <l>That you might not at last be fool'd,</l>
                     <l>And all your pains for nothing spend.</l>
                     <l>Some things there be if we begin<note place="margin">1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 15.1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc></desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>At the wrong end, they will not take;</l>
                     <l>But out in vain our time we spin,</l>
                     <l>And of them we no work can make.</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:152495:25"/>
                     <l> If Cart before the Horse we set,</l>
                     <l>Tho <hi>Haight, Gee, Whoe, Hut, Ha,</hi> we cry;</l>
                     <l>Yet something always still doth let,</l>
                     <l>And unremov'd the load will lie.</l>
                     <l>And if a Skein of Thread you take,</l>
                     <l>And with the wrong end think to winde,</l>
                     <l>You'll ravel, and your Thread will break,</l>
                     <l>And never can your Skein untwine.</l>
                     <l>Therefore had we (as oft we've found)</l>
                     <l>When thus our work is to no end,</l>
                     <l>As good our heels against the ground</l>
                     <l>To knock, as thus our time to spend.</l>
                     <l>And farther, this is common too,</l>
                     <l>Besure that if two ways there be,</l>
                     <l>One and the self-same work to do;</l>
                     <l>The right we miss, the wrong take we.</l>
                     <l>Just so 'tis here; two ways there are</l>
                     <l>To do good works, and to live well;</l>
                     <l>The one by faith,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.33.</note> that gift so rare,</l>
                     <l>Which onely in new hearts doth dwell.</l>
                     <l>The other is by Natures Light,</l>
                     <l>Joyn'd with some carnal Knowledge too,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Out of Gods written Law so bright;</l>
                     <l>And thus men think good works to do.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.5, 6. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But all in vain, in vain, alas!</l>
                     <l>For backward now these men do drive;</l>
                     <l>Their work they'l never bring to pass,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.30, 31, 32.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Though out their very hearts they strive.</l>
                     <l>It cannot be, so Christ doth say;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Except you shall abide in me,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 15.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Like Branches dead and cast away</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You are, and fruitless you will be.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But if in me abide you shall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Abundant fruit you forth shall bring:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152495:25"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But else you can do nought at all,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If close to me you do not cling.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>O that the World this Truth did know!</l>
                     <l>But Priest and People here are blind;</l>
                     <l>Most Priests the People this don't show;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 42.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor to them do this Knot untwine.</l>
                     <l>I know right-well they often teach</l>
                     <l>Of Faith, Repentance, and a Change;</l>
                     <l>And of Conversion too they preach:</l>
                     <l>Therefore you'll say my words are strange.</l>
                     <l>But mark what now to you I say;</l>
                     <l>'Tis true of these things they do speak,</l>
                     <l>And preach, but 'tis in such a way,</l>
                     <l>That it the heart can never break.</l>
                     <l>Nor do they plainly make't appear</l>
                     <l>That all the world are dead in sin;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 1.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 2.12. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor make each Mothers Child to hear</l>
                     <l>One dram of Grace they han't within.</l>
                     <l>Nor one good work that do they can,</l>
                     <l>Until the mighty God above,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 14.1. <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Do change the heart that is in man,</l>
                     <l>By that same Faith that works by Love.</l>
                     <l>They Faith do preach, and works also;</l>
                     <l>But there's no Life in what they say;</l>
                     <l>And on confusedly they go,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.10 11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That few by them can learn the way.</l>
                     <l>They do not strive to make men see,</l>
                     <l>That till in them this Change be wrought,</l>
                     <l>Like to the barren dead Fig-Tree,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>They never yet good fruit forth brought.</l>
                     <l>And why?<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 2.13.</note> Because they strangers are</l>
                     <l>Themselves, unto a heart made new;</l>
                     <l>And so this work of grace so rare,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 3.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Within their Gardens never grew.</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152495:26"/>
                     <l> I'll say no more, but onely so,</l>
                     <l>Do you your selves take heed you lay</l>
                     <l>A good foundation first below,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That on it safely build you may.</l>
                     <l>For if your works do not proceed</l>
                     <l>From a new heart,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15.</note> and grace within,</l>
                     <l>They never will be good indeed,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet in Gods fight worth a Pin.</l>
                     <l>They will no better be than loss,</l>
                     <l>Though once to you they seemed gain;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil</hi> 3.7, 8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea, you shall see them dung and dross,</l>
                     <l>If Christ to know you do attain.</l>
                     <l>But if your work from faith do flow,</l>
                     <l>From grace,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 3.21.</note> and from that union sweet</l>
                     <l>Wi<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc></desc>
                        </gap>h God and Jesus Christ also,</l>
                     <l>God in those works will with you meet:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.25.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And fill your hearts with comforts true,</l>
                     <l>So high,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.21, 23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23.</note> so full, so sweet, so rare;</l>
                     <l>That by them you may take a view,</l>
                     <l>What Joys at his Right Hand there are.</l>
                     <l>So Christ hath said: <hi>If you me love,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And my Commands keep and obey;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I and the Father from above,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Will come to you, ev'n day by day:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And you your selves belov'd shall be;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And we to you will manifest</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our selves, and our abode shall be</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With you, in which you will be blest.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And farther, I am bold to say,</l>
                     <l>If from that faith that works by love,</l>
                     <l>You hi Commands strive to obey,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.15, 16</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>From Heav'n to you he'll send the Dove.</l>
                     <l>Which will so sweetly on you show'r</l>
                     <l>Refreshing Dews of heav'nly grace;</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152495:26"/>
                     <l> That from on high you shall have pow'r</l>
                     <l>On earth with joy to run your Race.</l>
                     <l>And this will also be your Guide,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.26.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of truth to lead you in the way;</l>
                     <l>So that your foot shall never slide,</l>
                     <l>Because you'l walk in light of day.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 11.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Besides, a Comforter most sweet,</l>
                     <l>To you this heav'nly Dove will be,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 14.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>In troubles all, with which you meet;</l>
                     <l>And from them all 'twill set you free.</l>
                     <l>And all his Paths then Pleasantness</l>
                     <l>Will be, his Ways will then be Peace;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in them you he'll always bless,</l>
                     <l>And from all bondage you release.</l>
                     <l>For then to his Commands will he</l>
                     <l>Your hearts so sweetly suit alway,</l>
                     <l>That grievous they will seldom be;<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 3.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay Joy 'twill be them to obey.</l>
                     <l>Thus have I now bestow'd on you</l>
                     <l>The greatest part of my Advice;</l>
                     <l>What I advise, I hope you'll do;</l>
                     <l>And on my Counsel set a price.</l>
                     <l>For be you sure these Lines were pen'd</l>
                     <l>With Tears and Pray'rs to God on high,</l>
                     <l>That with them he'd his Blessing send,</l>
                     <l>Your hearts to change and mend thereby.</l>
                     <l>And now I should take leave indeed,</l>
                     <l>But that, (my Hearts) I still suppose</l>
                     <l>A little more Advice you'll need,</l>
                     <l>Before this my discourse I close.</l>
                     <l>And therefore I a few things more</l>
                     <l>Shall adde, to what's already said;</l>
                     <l>That they may lie by you in store,</l>
                     <l>When I within my Grave am laid.</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:152495:27"/>
                     <l> And first, Let me injoyn you all,</l>
                     <l>If God so merciful shall be,</l>
                     <l>As any one of you to call,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.6, 7.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>His love and grace in Christ to see:</l>
                     <l>Which of you first is call'd, I say,</l>
                     <l>And chang'd by his converting grace,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O see that for the rest thou pray,</l>
                     <l>That they like thee may Christ embrace.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Dear Child! Thou which art that first-born</l>
                     <l>By grace, of all thy Fathers seed,</l>
                     <l>And seest the rest all lie forlorn,</l>
                     <l>Still wrapt up in old <hi>Adam</hi>'s weed.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 3.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O Child, pray, pray, and pray again,</l>
                     <l>That God in Grace would on them look,</l>
                     <l>And wash their Souls from that foul stain</l>
                     <l>Of sin,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.20.</note> and write them in his Book.</l>
                     <l>And use all means to do them good,</l>
                     <l>To make them see that they are lost;</l>
                     <l>And for what cause Christ shed his blood,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.18, 19. <hi>Psal.</hi> 14.1, 2</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And what a price Redemption cost.</l>
                     <l>For these things yet they cannot see,</l>
                     <l>And thou these things dost know full well,</l>
                     <l>Thy Christ hath made them plain to thee,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.2.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all the world thou canst them tell.</l>
                     <l>Now therefore strive to make them plain</l>
                     <l>Before their Eyes, that by Gods grace,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.32.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>They unconvinc'd may not remain,</l>
                     <l>But see the Light with open face.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Isa.</hi> 2.3. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And draw them out along with thee,</l>
                     <l>To all good Opportunities;</l>
                     <l>For thou well know'st how sweet they be,</l>
                     <l>But they as yet are not so wise,</l>
                     <l>Thy Senses all, as yet they want;</l>
                     <l>Thy Sight, thy Taste, thy Hearing too;</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:152495:27"/>
                     <l> Thy Smell, thy Feeling,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14.</note> these they han't</l>
                     <l>When they unto the Means do go:</l>
                     <l>And therefore can't that sweetness find,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.103. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.162.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As thou dost, in the means of grace,</l>
                     <l>Nor can their hearts be so inclin'd,</l>
                     <l>With greediness it to embrace.</l>
                     <l>Again, Let me you all advise,</l>
                     <l>If God this Change shall work in you,</l>
                     <l>That what you know,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 13.17.</note> you would be wise</l>
                     <l>The same most faithfully to do.</l>
                     <l>For if you practise heartily,</l>
                     <l>What God to you makes manifest;</l>
                     <l>Then He'll make known, ev'n by and by,</l>
                     <l>The Bosom-Secrets of his Brest.</l>
                     <l>And his whole Counsel you shall see;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 20.27.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea, nothing from you he will hide;</l>
                     <l>His Privy Council you shall be,</l>
                     <l>His heart to you he'll open wide.</l>
                     <l>So saith our Jesus to us all;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If my Commands you keep and do,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 15.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Not Servants I, but Friends you call;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And as with Friends, I'll deal with you.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Lord, the secrets of his mind;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Unto his Servants will not tell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But to his Friends he is so kind,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 15.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To shew what in his heart doth dwell.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So all things which our Christ hath seen,</l>
                     <l>And of his Father heard also;</l>
                     <l>Though secrets they of old have been,</l>
                     <l>Yet these his Friends shall surely know.</l>
                     <l>So <hi>David,</hi> that good man, could say,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.98, 99.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I than my Teachers am more wise,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Because thy Laws I do obey,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And them to keep, at midnight rise.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:152495:28"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall I</hi> (saith God) <hi>from Abram hide</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Geu.</hi> 18.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The thing which I intend to do;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Since be all his will teach and guide,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My ways to know, and keep also?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And he that doth my Father's will,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Doctrine he</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>shall know;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 7.17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And he to judge shall have the skill,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whether 'tis from above or no.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For if the Eye but single be,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Body will be full of light;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22, 23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But if the Eye corrupt you see,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Body will be dark as night.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And one thing more I shall commend,</l>
                     <l>As that which is the onely way,</l>
                     <l>To bring you to that blessed end,</l>
                     <l>His ways to know, and to obey.</l>
                     <l>You must your wisdom lay aside,</l>
                     <l>And your own strength you must deny;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For your own Wisdom's a blind Guide,</l>
                     <l>And your own strength is but a Lye.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Job</hi> 32.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>You by your wisdom can't attain,</l>
                     <l>Not one good Truth truly to know;</l>
                     <l>Nor all the strength that doth remain</l>
                     <l>In you,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.7.</note> the least Command can't do.</l>
                     <l>For first, your wisdom's enmity</l>
                     <l>To God, and doth against him fight;</l>
                     <l>And doth oppose rebelliously</l>
                     <l>Against his Laws, and that true Light.</l>
                     <l>And therefore Fools become you must,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>If ever you think to be wise;</l>
                     <l>And lay your wisdom in the dust,</l>
                     <l>And see what darkness in it lies.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay farther, you must Children be,</l>
                     <l>As well as Fools; yea, small ones too;</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:152495:28"/>
                     <l> Like such which from the Brest you see</l>
                     <l>New taken, that can scarcely go.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whom shall we teach our Knowledge true?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 28.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>VVhom shall we make to understand</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Our Doctrine? Such as weaned new</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Are from the Brest, and led by th' hand.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And he that shall Gods Kingdom take,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Must take it as a little Child;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Or else he can no entrance make:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>None enters but the Meek and Mild.</l>
                     <l>So <hi>David,</hi> that good man, could say,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Meek he will in Judgement guide;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 25.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Humble he will teach his way;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So as their Feet shall never slide.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis this the wise men of our Age,</l>
                     <l>That makes to stumble and to fall;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis this our Rabbies wise and sage,</l>
                     <l>That makes so dark and blind-fold all.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea those blind Priests of these our days,</l>
                     <l>Their minds have darkned like a Cloud,</l>
                     <l>That they can't see the Sun's bright Rays,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18, 19. <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Cause of their Parts they are so proud.</l>
                     <l>'Tis this that all men wrongs indeed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc></desc>
                        </gap>at our sweet Christ han't humble made,</l>
                     <l>That they may see their pinching need</l>
                     <l>Of his prophetick teaching Trade.</l>
                     <l>And hence it is that Christ full low</l>
                     <l>In us doth lay this wisdom proud,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And daily doth it overthrow,</l>
                     <l>And makes it like a dusky Cloud.</l>
                     <l>And hence it is in this our Age,</l>
                     <l>Of those great wonders wrought by's hand,</l>
                     <l>Poor Babes the depth can only gage,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.25. <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But wise men can't them understand.</l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152495:29"/>
                     <l>'Tis hence that he to foolishness<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The wisdom of this world doth bring;</l>
                     <l>Because thereby men cannot guess,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.55, 56.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That He's both Prophet, Priest, and King.</l>
                     <l>'Tis hence that he doth backward turn</l>
                     <l>Wise men,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 44.25.</note> and makes Diviners mad;</l>
                     <l>That they like Dogs with madness gurn,</l>
                     <l>And at his doings are full sad.</l>
                     <l>But on the other side, I say,</l>
                     <l>If you shall Meek and Humble be,</l>
                     <l>And shall aside your wisdom lay,</l>
                     <l>Then you the Light shall clearly see.</l>
                     <l>For if the blindness of your mind<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.2.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>You truly feel, and shall see clear</l>
                     <l>That you Gods Truths can never find,</l>
                     <l>Unless to you reveal'd they are:<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And humbly thus to Christ shall go,</l>
                     <l>And sue unto him for his grace;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then all his Truths he'll make you know,</l>
                     <l>And them you'll see with open face.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.27.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And such a Teaching Christ to you,</l>
                     <l>Will at all times unto you be,</l>
                     <l>That to one Sermon you can't go,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 54.13. <hi>Psal.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.130.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But still more heav'nly Truth you'll see.</l>
                     <l>Nor shall you any Chapter read,</l>
                     <l>Nor one good Meeting e'er attend,</l>
                     <l>But some Truth to supply your need,</l>
                     <l>He there into your hearts will fend.</l>
                     <l>Again, I say in the next place,</l>
                     <l>If you likewise your strength deny,</l>
                     <l>And wholly lean upon his grace,</l>
                     <l>Then he'll you strengthen by and by.</l>
                     <l>So saith Saint <hi>Paul; VVhen weak am I,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then am I strong in Gods own strength;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:152495:29"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gods strength in weakness still doth lie,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The weak shall strong be made at length.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therefore in my infirmities</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Most gladly I'll rejoyce,</hi> saith he,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Because in me though weakness lies,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Yet I thereby his strength shall see.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay, God himself the same doth speak;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sufficient for thee is my Grace,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My strength's made perfect in the weak,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When truly they the same embrace.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Again, Let me advise you all,</l>
                     <l>If you that blessed Life would live,</l>
                     <l>That Life which Heav'n on Earth we call,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 1.1, 2.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which God to some sweet Souls doth give.</l>
                     <l>Then give your selves with all your might,</l>
                     <l>To do your Fathers work and will;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 4.34.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Make it your bus'ness and delight</l>
                     <l>His mind and pleasure to fulfill.</l>
                     <l>Count it your onely work I say,</l>
                     <l>That you have here below to do,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your Fathers will for to obey,</l>
                     <l>Though you thereby do all forgo.</l>
                     <l>Your meat and drink now let it be,</l>
                     <l>To do his will ev'n all your days;</l>
                     <l>So shall you taste, and also see,</l>
                     <l>Sweet Comforts flowing from his ways.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For this a certain Truth you'll find,</l>
                     <l>That when with all your strength &amp; might</l>
                     <l>To do his will you are inclin'd,</l>
                     <l>Making his ways your whole delight:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 1.2.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then, then, I say, and then alone,</l>
                     <l>The sweetness of his ways you'l know;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Job</hi> 22.26, 27, 28. 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 31.21</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But until then you'll always groan,</l>
                     <l>And under yoaks and burthens go,</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:152495:30"/>
                     <l> So saith the Prophet wise and grave,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If that you shall in God alone</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 37.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Delight your selves, then you shall have</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Of him your hearts desires each one.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And on the other side, we know</l>
                     <l>There is a curse to them that shall<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 48.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be negligent Gods work to do,</l>
                     <l>That doubtless will upon them fall.</l>
                     <l>We think (poor fools!) if we should give</l>
                     <l>Our selves, our hearts, and all our might,</l>
                     <l>Wholly to God, like Saints to live,</l>
                     <l>And onely make him our delight;</l>
                     <l>That then, at least whilst here we dwell</l>
                     <l>Upon the earth, sure lose we shall</l>
                     <l>Our ease, our gain, and such a deal</l>
                     <l>Of good, that here would us befall.</l>
                     <l>And therefore we prudential are,</l>
                     <l>One corner of our hearts to save,</l>
                     <l>To serve our selves, and so to share</l>
                     <l>With God, lest he the whole should have.</l>
                     <l>Some part of time, and heart, and strength,</l>
                     <l>We are content him to allow;</l>
                     <l>But that he should have all at length,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.26.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O this against the stream doth row.</l>
                     <l>But O poor hearts! this is the thing</l>
                     <l>That us of Heav'n on Earth deprives;</l>
                     <l>And doth our hearts to sorrow bring</l>
                     <l>Full oft, i'th' compass of our lives:</l>
                     <l>And makes Gods pleasant ways to be</l>
                     <l>Ruff, rugged, sowr, and hard to bear;</l>
                     <l>Whereas if that our hearts were free,</l>
                     <l>They would be sweet beyond compare.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And now I should conclude indeed,</l>
                     <l>But that a word or two remains;</l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:152495:30"/>
                     <l> Which if I write, and if you read,</l>
                     <l>It may be still worth all our pains.</l>
                     <l>One word is this, I you advise</l>
                     <l>That you would very careful be,</l>
                     <l>And circumspect in any wise,</l>
                     <l>About your keeping companie:</l>
                     <l>Of such Companions still make choice,</l>
                     <l>As truly practise what they know;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 119.63. 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 1.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And in their friendship most rejoyce,</l>
                     <l>Within whose hearts true faith doth grow.</l>
                     <l>With sober Souls, that faithful are,</l>
                     <l>That know the weight and pow'r of sin,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.24.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And such as can to you declare</l>
                     <l>How good their God to them hath bin.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 66.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>With such who their own hearts do know,</l>
                     <l>Their faults and frailties manifold;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And for the same have lain full low,</l>
                     <l>As they to you have often told.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 32.3, 4 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>With such, the Tempters craft that know,</l>
                     <l>His gins, his darts, his subtilty;</l>
                     <l>Acquainted with his wiles also,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 6.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As having oft smarted thereby.</l>
                     <l>With such as strict and circumspect<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are in their words, and actions too;</l>
                     <l>And quickly are by Conscience check'd,</l>
                     <l>When the least thing amiss they do.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>With such your selves associate,</l>
                     <l>And daily keep their company;</l>
                     <l>Decline not such at any rate,</l>
                     <l>For you'll much good receive thereby.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And out of these, chuse one or two,</l>
                     <l>That wise, and fast, and faithful are;</l>
                     <l>To whom, and that with safety too,</l>
                     <l>You may your hearts freely declare.</l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:152495:31"/>
                     <l> Because their hearts most sweetly be</l>
                     <l>Match'd, pair'd, and suited to your own,</l>
                     <l>By that great Workman, because he</l>
                     <l>The same things hath to both made known.</l>
                     <l>To these your hearts wide open lay,</l>
                     <l>Your sins, your griefs, temptations, all</l>
                     <l>Your frailties,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.16.</note> and together pray</l>
                     <l>For help, and comfort find you shall.</l>
                     <l>Twill ease your hearts, and grief asswage,</l>
                     <l>Through grace, and healing you shall find;</l>
                     <l>Which will your hearts to God engage,</l>
                     <l>When he'll with oyl your wounds up-bind.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 61.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And as I counsel and advise</l>
                     <l>You all to keep such company;</l>
                     <l>So I'll you tell, contrariwise,</l>
                     <l>What sort of men I'd have you fly.</l>
                     <l>All such Professors as you see</l>
                     <l>Light,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.16.</note> frothy, loose, airy, unsound;</l>
                     <l>All Notionists; for such men be</l>
                     <l>All Head,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.4, 5</note> no Heart in them is found.</l>
                     <l>These men have Notions quaint and rare,</l>
                     <l>And they with gallant words can talk;</l>
                     <l>But all's but froth,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18.</note> meer words and air;</l>
                     <l>For though they speak, they do not walk.</l>
                     <l>They want in them that savour sweet,</l>
                     <l>That Oyl,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Mark</hi> 9.50.</note> that Juyce, that Sap of Grace,</l>
                     <l>With which in all good Souls you meet,</l>
                     <l>And read it in their very face.</l>
                     <l>And if their Notions should be right,</l>
                     <l>Yet you small good shall gain thereby;<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But if against the Truth they fight,</l>
                     <l>Then you by them in danger lie.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Besides, if with these men you trade,</l>
                     <l>Like them you'll light and frothy be;</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:152495:31"/>
                     <l> And lose your Salt; yea, quickly fade,</l>
                     <l>And wither like a sapless Tree.</l>
                     <l>And hardly you'll get up again,</l>
                     <l>Unto your former frame of heart;</l>
                     <l>And though you tug and strive amain,</l>
                     <l>Before you can, 'twill cost you smart.</l>
                     <l>Again, All such as formal are,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That for meer Forms and Outsides stand,</l>
                     <l>And for the Pow'r have little care,</l>
                     <l>Avoid these on the other hand.</l>
                     <l>For though these think they zealous be</l>
                     <l>For God, and for his Worship too;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.20, 21.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet from Religion they are free,</l>
                     <l>And nought that's truly good they do.</l>
                     <l>Because these their Religion place</l>
                     <l>Not in the Kernel, but the shell;</l>
                     <l>Not in that inward work of grace,</l>
                     <l>By which Christ in the heart doth dwell.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But in some outside things alone,</l>
                     <l>Which though ev'n God himself appoints;</l>
                     <l>Yet Christs they make of them each one,</l>
                     <l>Instead of him whom God anoints.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>My Children, don't mistake me here,</l>
                     <l>As though against all Forms I speak;</l>
                     <l>For I have often made it clear,</l>
                     <l>That way true Worship soon will break.</l>
                     <l>But that which I against do drive,</l>
                     <l>Is, when men with the pow'r of grace,</l>
                     <l>The outside part of Worship strive,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.4. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.24, 26.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To set, at least, in equal place.</l>
                     <l>These foolish are, and blind also,</l>
                     <l>Yea, saltless Souls, sapless and dry,</l>
                     <l>For nothing rightly do they know,</l>
                     <l>And therefore leave their company.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152495:32"/>
                     <l> For you'll no good amongst them get,</l>
                     <l>Whate'er's their way they do profess;</l>
                     <l>And though much time apart you set</l>
                     <l>With them, you'll profit less and less.</l>
                     <l>And of this sort of Formalists,</l>
                     <l>In all our several ways and kind</l>
                     <l>Of Professors, you cannot miss</l>
                     <l>In each great store of these to find.</l>
                     <l>And 'twill be fo, till with his fan,</l>
                     <l>Christ Jesus hath gone o'er them all,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And then like Chaff, do what they can,</l>
                     <l>They'll flie away,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.8.</note> stumble, and fall.</l>
                     <l>Again, With Christians when you meet,</l>
                     <l>See that your time you well do spend;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.29.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Don't fall into Discourse unmeet,</l>
                     <l>That onely doth to by-things tend.</l>
                     <l>Don't about forms and words dispute,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet for needless Questions strive,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.14, 23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Seeking each other to confute;</l>
                     <l>Your Souls by this will never thrive.</l>
                     <l>Neither affect high things to speak,</l>
                     <l>Nor things in which you do not live,</l>
                     <l>For so beyond your line you'll break,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 131.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 4.20.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To which no blessing God will give.</l>
                     <l>But let your talk of such things be,</l>
                     <l>As savour well, and chiefly tend</l>
                     <l>Your Souls of sin and deaah to free,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.29.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And further you your lives to mend.</l>
                     <l>And such discourse as gives you light</l>
                     <l>To see your base deceitful heart;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And Satan's wiles, and ev'ry sleight,</l>
                     <l>By which (if snar'd) your Souls will smart.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And lets you see Christs fulness too,</l>
                     <l>The Creatures vanity and loss;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 1.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:152495:32"/>
                     <l> That if them both compare you do,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.8. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The latter will appear but dross.</l>
                     <l>Such talk too, as will sinners wound,</l>
                     <l>And broken hearts doth heal and bind;</l>
                     <l>'Tis this that makes men right and sound,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 50.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And of a sweet and sober mind.</l>
                     <l>Christ in this talk with you will meet,</l>
                     <l>Warming your hearts, making them glow,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 64.5. <hi>Luk</hi> 24.32.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That you from their communion sweet,</l>
                     <l>Refresh'd and chear'd away shall go.</l>
                     <l>Before this point aside I lay,</l>
                     <l>About your keeping Company,</l>
                     <l>Another word still I shall say,</l>
                     <l>Wherein some weight and stress may lie.</l>
                     <l>When you upon your legs are set,</l>
                     <l>And peace with God have now obtain'd,</l>
                     <l>And nothing doth your Comforts let,</l>
                     <l>Because the Devil up is chain'd.</l>
                     <l>Don't spend your time as formerly,</l>
                     <l>With such as high in faith are grown,</l>
                     <l>But now your selves to th' Babes apply,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.1.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And such as under Burthens groan.</l>
                     <l>Now feed the Babes, give them the Brest,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Thes.</hi> 5.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And nurse and tittle up the Young;</l>
                     <l>And shew the weary Souls their Rest,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 28.12. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Their feeble knees and hands make strong.</l>
                     <l>And labour now dead Souls to wake,</l>
                     <l>That yet lie fast asleep in sin;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.14 <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.29.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And strive their stony hearts to break,</l>
                     <l>That so their lost Souls you may win.</l>
                     <l>And if in this way you shall go,</l>
                     <l>To wake the dead, the wounded heal,</l>
                     <l>And weak make strong, more good you'll do,</l>
                     <l>I truly think, by a great deal,</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:152495:33"/>
                     <l> Than if your time you always spend</l>
                     <l>With Saints that strong and skilful are,</l>
                     <l>Their helps to crave, and yours to lend,</l>
                     <l>And o'er each other take the care.</l>
                     <l>I know for both there is a time,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccles.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For strong and weak, for old and young;</l>
                     <l>But yet your Musick's dainty Chime,</l>
                     <l>Sounds best the broken Hearts among.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.15.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And sure I am, more Comfort you</l>
                     <l>By far to your own hearts will find;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Job</hi> 29.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea, and more profit you'll get too,</l>
                     <l>If to this way you are inclin'd.</l>
                     <l>Enough of this, I'll say no more:</l>
                     <l>But yet I have another thing,</l>
                     <l>Which if you keep by you in store,</l>
                     <l>Much good unto you it may bring.</l>
                     <l>'Tis this, I must you warning give,</l>
                     <l>Of one base cursed bitter Root;</l>
                     <l>Which poysons all where it doth live,</l>
                     <l>And where it can but set the foot.</l>
                     <l>'Tis Cov'toufness, that cursed Brat,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 5.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That Canker-worm, that doth devour</l>
                     <l>All Grace, all Good, and lays it flat,</l>
                     <l>Where it doth get but Head or Pow'r.</l>
                     <l>First, This will make your Graces all,</l>
                     <l>That green have been,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.13.</note> and shining bright,</l>
                     <l>To wither, pine, wax dead, and fall,</l>
                     <l>And that in open view and sight.</l>
                     <l>Again, your hearts pierce through it will,</l>
                     <l>With divers cares,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9.</note> temptations,</l>
                     <l>And all your Lives this Root will fill</l>
                     <l>With gall, grief, and vexations.</l>
                     <l>Besides, a cursed Train it draws</l>
                     <l>Of sins and vices with it too;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:152495:33"/>
                     <l> Which on poor Conscience daily gnaws,</l>
                     <l>And doth the gracious Soul undo.</l>
                     <l>Lastly, 'twill spoil your savour sweet,</l>
                     <l>Which should scent forth like <hi>Lebanon,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hos.</hi> 14.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To all with whom you live or meet,</l>
                     <l>You'll be as dry as any Bone.</l>
                     <l>Therefore this <hi>Colloquenquidine,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That soon will your good Pottage spoil,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 4.40.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Keep out, cast out o'th' heart betime,</l>
                     <l>Else afterward it will you foil.</l>
                     <l>But though of this I warn you all,</l>
                     <l>That you be not insnar'd thereby;</l>
                     <l>Yet I must needs upon you call,</l>
                     <l>That you in slothfulness don't lie.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.11. 2 <hi>Thes.</hi> 3.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But in some honest Calling see</l>
                     <l>You live, and to it set your hand,</l>
                     <l>That in it you employ'd may be,</l>
                     <l>For this doth suit with Gods Command.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ephes.</hi> 4.28.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yea farther, I you counsel give,</l>
                     <l>To follow it with all your might,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccles.</hi> 9.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That you a good full Trade may drive,</l>
                     <l>For this is pleasing in Gods sight.</l>
                     <l>But yet take heed, take heed, take heed,</l>
                     <l>That with your wit, and strength, &amp; hand,</l>
                     <l>(All which must be emploi'd indeed)</l>
                     <l>Your heart don't joyn, &amp; with them band;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 62.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Its own design to bring to pass,</l>
                     <l>And set up <hi>Mammon</hi> as its God:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O here take heed, my Babes! alas,</l>
                     <l>'Tis this that makes what's even, odd.</l>
                     <l>This also poisons all you do,</l>
                     <l>Ev'n all to which your hand you set;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.21. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.1, 2, 3, 4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>This brings a curse upon you too;</l>
                     <l>And with your Goods, the Devil you get.</l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:152495:34"/>
                     <l> I know it is the hardest thing</l>
                     <l>The hand closely at work to be</l>
                     <l>On earth,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.10.</note> and yet the heart on wing</l>
                     <l>Heav'n-ward,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 3.2.</note> and from the Earth set free.</l>
                     <l>And he that can command his heart</l>
                     <l>In this, and bend it to his Bow;</l>
                     <l>He's more the Master of his Art,</l>
                     <l>Than all in <hi>Oxford</hi>-streets that go.</l>
                     <l>And yet you must this Lesson learn,</l>
                     <l>Your hand with diligence to give</l>
                     <l>Unto your Calling,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.14</note> so to earn</l>
                     <l>That by which you and yours may live.</l>
                     <l>And the more diligent you are,</l>
                     <l>So that your heart be dis-engag'd,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.27.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>The better you and yours may fare,</l>
                     <l>And all your war's more eas'ly wag'd.</l>
                     <l>You may provide things honest too,</l>
                     <l>And good in all mens sight;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.17.</note> beside,</l>
                     <l>Well fed, well cloathed you may go,</l>
                     <l>And so may bid the world to slide.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.15 21. <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.20</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Again, you may the better feed</l>
                     <l>The Poor, and sweetly deal about</l>
                     <l>Your bounty, where you see there's need;</l>
                     <l>So you their love shan't go without.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.28.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And surely a more blessed thing</l>
                     <l>It is,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 20.35.</note> to give, than to receive;</l>
                     <l>The blessing of the Perishing</l>
                     <l>Shall on you come,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Job</hi> 29.13. <hi>Rev.</hi> 8.3, 4.</note> and to you cleave.</l>
                     <l>Besides, poor Saints, whose pray'rs do run</l>
                     <l>Each day and night unto the Throne,</l>
                     <l>You may relieve and help each one,</l>
                     <l>Which is to you a good seed sown.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Again, the greater sway you'll bear</l>
                     <l>I'th' place God points you out to dwell;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.24</note>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:152495:34"/>
                     <l> That what prophaneness shall appear</l>
                     <l>There, you may it the better quell.</l>
                     <l>Again, more time you then may spare</l>
                     <l>In Gods sweet worship to abide;</l>
                     <l>Without that base distracting care</l>
                     <l>That o'er your faithless hearts will slide.</l>
                     <l>More time to read, to praise, to pray,</l>
                     <l>In private by your selves alone;</l>
                     <l>More time with Christians you may stay,</l>
                     <l>When you do meet with them each one.</l>
                     <l>More time to hear, and Meetings go,</l>
                     <l>More time to stay when you be there;</l>
                     <l>More time to visit Friends also,</l>
                     <l>And see how it with them doth fare.</l>
                     <l>These are the ends that I propound,</l>
                     <l>Why in your Calling you should be</l>
                     <l>Most diligent and daily found,</l>
                     <l>If some good Call don't set you free.</l>
                     <l>But O take heed! take heed I say,</l>
                     <l>That whilst these things you do pretend,</l>
                     <l>You do not steer another way,</l>
                     <l>And quite unto another end.</l>
                     <l>Namely, that you might great become,</l>
                     <l>And rich, and high i'th' worlds account;</l>
                     <l>That you might bravely live at home,</l>
                     <l>And when abroad might all surmount.</l>
                     <l>That you might flaunt and tear about,</l>
                     <l>As you see some brave Sparks to do,</l>
                     <l>Where e'er they come, to make a rout,</l>
                     <l>Poor fools, and think 'tis gallant too.</l>
                     <l>Or else that your Posterity</l>
                     <l>Might bravely live when you are dead,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 49.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And have a name half up to th' Sky,</l>
                     <l>That so of you it might be said,</l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:152495:35"/>
                     <l> This was the old mans Providence,</l>
                     <l>That makes his Children live so well;</l>
                     <l>And though his Grave hath took him hence,</l>
                     <l>Yet still he hears this Tale some tell.</l>
                     <l>Take heed of such base ends, I say,</l>
                     <l>Which soon into your hearts may get;</l>
                     <l>And if you watch not night and day,</l>
                     <l>These footing in the same will set.</l>
                     <l>And poyson all your labours too;</l>
                     <l>And you and your Posterity</l>
                     <l>Gods curse will blast,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 73.19, 20. <hi>Prov.</hi> 16.7.</note> and quite undo,</l>
                     <l>And root you out from under th' Sky,</l>
                     <l>I have another word to say,</l>
                     <l>Before this point let pass I shall;</l>
                     <l>Do you give ear to it I pray,</l>
                     <l>It may be useful to you all.</l>
                     <l>If you your Calling follow close,</l>
                     <l>With honest care and diligence,</l>
                     <l>And for a blessing have recourse</l>
                     <l>To God,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 19.17.</note> and yet he don't dispence</l>
                     <l>His blessing so upon the work</l>
                     <l>Of your own hands, but still you see</l>
                     <l>A secret curse through all to lurk,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And you at this much sadded be;</l>
                     <l>Because so fast you cannot thrive</l>
                     <l>I'th' world, as some (less painful do)</l>
                     <l>Although you faithfully do strive</l>
                     <l>And daily beg Gods blessing too:</l>
                     <l>Then first the cause do you search out,</l>
                     <l>Why God his blessing doth suspend;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.40.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Through Conscience make both rack &amp; rout,</l>
                     <l>That you may see't, and so amend.</l>
                     <l>And if by search you cannot find</l>
                     <l>What is the cause you do not thrive,</l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:152495:35"/>
                     <l> Because your sin hath made you blind,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.19.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then go to God, and with him strive;</l>
                     <l>To shew you what the cause may be,</l>
                     <l>Pray hard, and to the Promise fly,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 19.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That he would ope your eyes to see</l>
                     <l>Where curfed <hi>Achan</hi> close doth lie.</l>
                     <l>But if God should not presently</l>
                     <l>Shew you the Cause, then wait a while,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.3.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Still pray, believe, and to him cry;</l>
                     <l>And then at last he in will smile,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Isa.</hi> 30.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And cast on <hi>Achan</hi>'s head his lot,</l>
                     <l>And out the cursed Villain bring;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Josh.</hi> 7.18.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then stone the Wretch, and spare him not,</l>
                     <l>O don't forbear at him to fling;</l>
                     <l>And don't you cry, as <hi>David</hi> cry'd</l>
                     <l>For his white Boy, <hi>O Absalon,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18.33.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Son, that I for thee had dy'd!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O Abfalon, my Son, my Son!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But if no <hi>Achan</hi> should appear,</l>
                     <l>When you the means thus used have,</l>
                     <l>Then for the matter take no care;</l>
                     <l>Yet still do you his Blessing crave:</l>
                     <l>And cheerfully wait on him still;</l>
                     <l>The time it may be come is not,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>John</hi> 2.4.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>When he your prayers answer will,</l>
                     <l>And your own askings you allot.</l>
                     <l>Or else his end may be to try</l>
                     <l>How you'll submit unto his hand,</l>
                     <l>And be content in poverty,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As well as in a flowing Land.</l>
                     <l>And when your hearts unto his Bow</l>
                     <l>He thus hath bent, a blessing then</l>
                     <l>On all your Labours he'll bestow,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.12</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And to your prayers say, Amen.</l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:152495:36"/>
                     <l> But if he should with Poverty</l>
                     <l>Still all along you exercise;</l>
                     <l>Then know it for a certainty,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.27.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>It is because he's onely wise;</l>
                     <l>And knows your frailties all; yea, he</l>
                     <l>Knows how his mercies you'd abuse,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 49.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And Blessings Curses soon would be,</l>
                     <l>When them you know not how to use,<note place="margin">Eccles. <hi>5.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And then, because he loves you dear,</l>
                     <l>And knows that this condition's best<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccles.</hi> 5.13.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>For your immortal Souls welfare,</l>
                     <l>In this estate he'd have you rest.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mark</hi> 10.25.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O Children, therefore be content,</l>
                     <l>If you into this state shall fall;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.11, 12</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And let not your poor hearts resent,</l>
                     <l>As if you far'd the worst of all.</l>
                     <l>No, no; I tell you 'tis not so;</l>
                     <l>God loves you, as I said before;</l>
                     <l>And if you walk as you should do,</l>
                     <l>He heav'nly Blessings hath in store.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Psal.</hi> 50.23.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And he'll make up abundantly</l>
                     <l>Your outward wants with inward Grace,</l>
                     <l>And with his Spirit you supply,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mark</hi> 10.30. <hi>Act.</hi> 20.24.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>That sweetly you may run your Race.</l>
                     <l>For if your hearts with faith he fill,</l>
                     <l>Although you live and norning have,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet you (as if the world at will</l>
                     <l>You had) shall sweetly live, and brave.</l>
                     <l>Though in this world you be but poor,</l>
                     <l>Yet if you rich in faith shall be,</l>
                     <l>And Heirs o'th' Kingdom evermore,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>O happy then, thrice happy ye!</l>
                     <l>Besides, consider 'twas the state</l>
                     <l>In which God put his onely Son;</l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:152495:36"/>
                     <l> So as he liv'd but at your rate,</l>
                     <l>Whilst his sweet course i'th' world he run.</l>
                     <l>Foxes had holes, the Birds had Nests,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.20.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>But yet the glorious Son of man</l>
                     <l>Had not a place his head to rest,</l>
                     <l>Though on his head the Dove did stand.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>This was th' Apostles portion too,</l>
                     <l>Those glorious Hero's of their Age,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 3.16.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who walk'd i'th' world here to and fro,</l>
                     <l>In a most heav'nly equipage.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.11.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And of those holy men of old,</l>
                     <l>That clad with Sheep and Goatskins were,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.37.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To keep their bodies from the Cold,</l>
                     <l>In Deserts wandring here and there:</l>
                     <l>Who oft in Dens and Caves did lie,</l>
                     <l>Of whom the world not worthy were;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.38.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>These this worlds glory did defie,</l>
                     <l>And now at Gods right hand they are.</l>
                     <l>This Path most Saints have soundly trod,</l>
                     <l>I think almost in ev'ry Age;</l>
                     <l>This Lot was lin'd them out by God,</l>
                     <l>As their sweet earthly heritage.</l>
                     <l>And now methinks this rugged way</l>
                     <l>So often trod, should grow more plain</l>
                     <l>To us that live i'th' Gospel-day,</l>
                     <l>And follow all this Heav'nly Train.</l>
                     <l>I have but one word more to give,</l>
                     <l>By way of Counsel to you all,</l>
                     <l>To teach you how you here should live,</l>
                     <l>And I to God commit you shall.</l>
                     <l>'Tis this: I'd have your carriage be</l>
                     <l>Kind, lovely, affable, and sweet,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.31, 32 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To High and Low, to Bond and Free;</l>
                     <l>To all with whom you live or meet.</l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:152495:37"/>
                     <l> Speak friendly, and act friendly too,</l>
                     <l>Yet so as Grace and Wisdom may<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Appear in all you speak and do:</l>
                     <l>O you had need for this to pray.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Col.</hi> 4.6.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And see that you do not comply</l>
                     <l>With fin,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.11.</note> or what is done amiss;</l>
                     <l>Nor unreproov'd yet let it lre,</l>
                     <l>Though fools may laugh at you for this.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.9.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And if you kind and courteous are,</l>
                     <l>With Wisdom, Grace, and Gravity;</l>
                     <l>Wise men good will to you will bear,</l>
                     <l>And persons vain will from you fly.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Job</hi> 29.8.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And this will stop the mouths of those</l>
                     <l>That else would say you're proud &amp; stout,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Psal.</hi> 69.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And none but Drunkards, I suppose,</l>
                     <l>Will dare at you to scoff and flout.</l>
                     <l>And if they should, yet certainly</l>
                     <l>Their Conscience will accuse,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.16.</note> and tell</l>
                     <l>Them, what they say is but a Lye,</l>
                     <l>And they shall smart for it in Hell.</l>
                     <l>Again, This way much honour you</l>
                     <l>Unto Religion sure may bring;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.27.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And you more good by far may do,</l>
                     <l>To bring in Souls to Christ your King.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Well now (my Babes) I finish'd have</l>
                     <l>What in my heart I had to say:</l>
                     <l>A Blessing on it I do crave,</l>
                     <l>That to your Souls do good it may.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And now the Blessing of that GOD</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That once within the Bush did dwell,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 33.13, 14, 15. <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 25, 26.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And which on</hi> Joseph'<hi>s Head abode,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Make you in Blessings to excell.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:37"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:38"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:152495:38"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>